<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short view of the Antinomian errours with a briefe and plaine answer to them, as the heads of them lye in order in the next page of this book : being a nest of cursed errors hatched by hereticks, fed and nourished by their proselites : being taken as they were flying abroad were brought as the eagle doth her young ones to see if they could endure to looke upon the sun-beams of truth with fixed eyes, the which they could not : were presently adjudged to be a bastard brood, and their necks chopt off, and their carkasses throwne to the dunghill.</title>
            <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30025</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38704</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17893946</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17893946</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106746</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30025)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106746)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1115:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short view of the Antinomian errours with a briefe and plaine answer to them, as the heads of them lye in order in the next page of this book : being a nest of cursed errors hatched by hereticks, fed and nourished by their proselites : being taken as they were flying abroad were brought as the eagle doth her young ones to see if they could endure to looke upon the sun-beams of truth with fixed eyes, the which they could not : were presently adjudged to be a bastard brood, and their necks chopt off, and their carkasses throwne to the dunghill.</title>
                  <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for Ed. Blakmore and Tho. Bankes, and are to be sold at the Angell in Pauls Church-yard ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Thomas Bakewell.</note>
                  <note>"Imprimatur Ja. Cranford."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Antinomianism.</term>
               <term>Heresies, Christian --  History --  Modern period, 1500-</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106746:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106746:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A ſhort View of the ANTINOMIAN ERROVRS: With a Briefe and plaine <hi>Anſwer</hi> to them, As the Heads of them lye in order in the next Page of this Booke.</p>
            <p>Being a neſt of curſed Errors hatched by Hereticks, fed and nouriſhed by their Proſelites; being taken as they were flying abroad were brought as the Eagle doth her young ones to ſee if they could endure to looke upon the Sun-beams of truth with fixed eyes, the which they could not; were preſently adjudged to be a Baſtard-brood, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> necks chopt off, and their carkaſſes throwne to the Dunghill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi> Ja. Cranford.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Beware of falſe Prophets which come to you in ſheeps cloathing; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly are ravening Wolves,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 7.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>There are certaine men crept in unawares, who were before of old ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this condemnation, ungodly men turning the grace of our God into laſciviouſneſſe,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jude 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>For when they ſpeake great ſwelling words of vanity, they allure through the luſts of the fleſh, through much wantonneſſe, thoſe that were cleane eſcaped from them who live in errour; for while they promiſe them li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Pet. 2, 18.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>Ed. Blakmore</hi> and <hi>Tho. Bankes,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Angell in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard and upon the top of <hi>Bridewell-ſtaires,</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:106746:2"/>
            <p n="1">1 THey hold that a man is juſtified as ſoon as he hath a being in the ſight of God, before they have any faith or calling.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Then they ſay, God cannot ſee their ſinne, for they are as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly righteous even as Chriſt himſelfe, as ſoone as they have any being, and faith doth but declare to them what was done in them before they had it, even as ſoone as they were borne.</p>
            <p n="3">3 This they know by revelation, or a bare Teſtimony, or ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, they ſay, from the Spirit of God, when as they deny the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or the ſanctifying worke of the Spirit of God, to be any meanes whereby they may come to know their juſtification; for ſo to doe, they ſay is the doctrine of our legall Teachers, which goe by markes and ſignes.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Then they being as righteous as Chriſt, they ſay, God doth not correct them for ſinne, neither can he doe it, but onely to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their faith.</p>
            <p n="5">5 They are freed they ſay, by the free grace of Chriſt, from the commanding power of the law of God, and they are diſcharged from all duty or obedience to it, and now the law is no rule to them, but what they doe is onely out of love unrequired, not as any duty, for they are freed from all by their free grace.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I have gathered both from their Sermons, and by conference with them? as alſo out of their books, which have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed privately amongſt themſelves.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106746:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>CHriſtian Reader, now in theſe laſt &amp; perilous dayes, the divel is very buſie to ſowe the Tares of Hereſies even in the Corn-field of Chriſt, eſpecially when men ſleep and heed him not; and therefore Christians had need to be circumspect &amp; watchfull, becauſe their adverſary the divel as a roaring lyon walketh about ſeeking whom he may devour, <hi>1 Pe. 5.8.</hi> Then be no more toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed too &amp; fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine by the ſleight of men and cunning craftineſſe, whereby they lye in waite to deceive, <hi>Ephe. 4.14.</hi> I ſay <hi>be not carried about with divers and ſtrange doctrines, for it is good that the heart be eſtabliſhed with grace,</hi> Heb. <hi>13.9.</hi> Watch ye, ſtand faſt in the faith, quit ye like men, and be ſtrong, take unto you the whole Armour of God, that ye may be able to ſtand; ſtand therefore having your loynes girt about with truth, <hi>Ephe. 6.</hi> and having laid the true foundation, which is Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>be ye root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and built up in him, and eſtabliſhed in the faith, as ye have been taught,</hi> Col. <hi>2.7.</hi> if ſo be ye have been taught by him as the truth is in Jeſus, <hi>Ephe. 4.</hi> I write unto you and exhort you, that you would earneſtly contend for the faith, that was once delivered unto the Saints, <hi>Jude 3.</hi> onely let your converſation be as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Gospell of Chriſt, and that ye ſtand faſt in one ſpirit with one mind, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving together for the faith of the Gospell, <hi>Phil. 2.27.</hi> and the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt you. <hi>They that truſt in the Lord ſhall be as Mount Zion, which cannot be moved but abideth for ever, Pſal. 125.</hi> it is true that <hi>offences muſt needs come, but woe be to that man by whom they come,</hi> Mat. <hi>18.7.</hi> for there must be alſo hereſies among you, that they which are approved may be made manifest, <hi>1 Cor. 11.9.</hi> then ſeeke no novelties or new doctrines, but rather stand in the wayes, and ſee and aske for the old pathes, where is the good way and walk ye in it, and ye ſhall find rest for your ſoules, <hi>Jer. 6.16.</hi> thinke of no other way to heaven, but that which our fathers have gone in before you, <hi>for the time is come that men will not endure ſound doctrine, but after their owne luſts they will heape up to themſelves teachers, having itching eares they will turne away their eares from the truth and ſhall be turned unto fables, but watch you in all things, 2</hi> Tim. <hi>4.3, 4, 5. Beloved, beleeve not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits whether they be of God, becauſe many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world 1</hi> John <hi>4.1.</hi> follow <hi>Paul</hi> but as he followes Chriſt, and be ye like the noble
<pb facs="tcp:106746:3"/>Bereans, who ſearched the Scriptures daily to ſee whether thoſe things were ſo, <hi>Acts 17.11.</hi> affect neither <hi>Paul,</hi> nor <hi>Apollos,</hi> nor <hi>Cephas,</hi> nor any other, but as they ground their doctrine on the cleere word of God, for ſeducers will labour to ſteale away your affections and your mony alſo, as <hi>Abſalom</hi> by flattery ſtole away the hearts of the men of Iſrael, <hi>2. Sam. 15.6.</hi> they will teach for hire and divine for money, <hi>Micah 3.11.</hi> but ſaith <hi>Paul, I ſeeke not yours but you, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>12.14.</hi> but ſeducers will creep into houſes about <hi>Moor-fields</hi> and other places, and lead captive ſilly women laden with their luſts, they will ſet upon thoſe that are led away with their luſts, who are ever learning, and never able to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, <hi>2 Tim. 3.6, 7.</hi> let no man deceive you, for with faire speeches they will deceive the hearts of the ſimple, who beleeve every thing, but the wiſe lookes well to his going, <hi>Prov. 14.15. thus through covetouſneſſe, they will with faigned words make merchandiſe of you, 2</hi> Pet. <hi>2.3.</hi> then heare thoſe that have renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſty, and doe not walke in craftineſſe nor handle the word of God deceitfully, but by manifeſtation of the truth, doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themſelves to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God, <hi>2 Cor. 4.2.</hi> who are not as many, who corrupt the Word of God, but as of ſincerity, but as of God, in the ſight of God, ſo ſpeak they in Chriſt, <hi>2 Cor. 2.17.</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, though we or an Angell of Heaven ſhall preach unto you any other Goſpell then that which we have preached unto you, let him be accurſed: I ſay againe, let him be accurſed, Gal. 1.8, 9.</hi> then take heed of the Antinomians new Gospell, who have caſt off all obedience to the law of God, who deſire to live without rule like ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> that they may take their full ſwing in ſinne under their damnable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that they have gotten free grace that hath freed them from all obedience to the law of God; but for thy information I have written this little booke, read it, and if thou receive any benefit or ſatisfaction, give God the praiſe and me the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of thy prayers, now unto him that is able to keep you from falling, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you faultleſſe before the preſence of his glory, with exceeding joy, to the onely wiſe God our Saviour, be glory and Majeſty, dominion and power, now and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord Jeſus,</hi> Thomas Bakewell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106746:3"/>
            <head>A ſhort view of the <hi>Antinomean</hi> Errours, with a Briefe Anſwer to them.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>They hold, that a man is justified as ſoone as he hath a being in the ſight of God, before faith or calling.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O this I anſwer, leaving the decrees and purpoſes of God to himſelfe as ſecret things, not belonging to us till we have faith and calling but to ſpeake as it is reveal'd, and according to our apprehenſion, both of the cauſes and time of a ſinners actuall juſtification, as it is reveal'd unto us in the Scripture.</p>
               <p>Firſt, we are ſaid to be juſtified by the blood of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. this is done by Chriſt as the meriting cauſe of our juſtification; <hi>He hath purchaſed his Church with his owne blood, Acts</hi> 20.28.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we are ſaid to be juſtified by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. <hi>Therefore as by the offence of one, judgement came upon all men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; even ſo by the righteouſneſſe of one, the free gift came upon all unto juctification of life:</hi> this is the formall cauſe of our juſtification; this righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is not that Inherent righteouſneſſe or ſanctification that is wrought in us by the Spirit of God, but it is that without us, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in Chriſt himſelfe that juſtifies us, for they are two diſtinct thing, it is called the righteouſneſſe of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Then they are very ignorant of Gods righteouſneſſe that goe about to eſtabliſh their owne righteouſneſſe, and have not ſubmitted themſelves to the righteouſneſſe of God, Rom.</hi> 10.3. <hi>Paul deſired not to be found in his owne righteouſneſſe, but in that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe of God by faith, Phil.</hi> 3.9. This righteouſneſſe without us being imputed to us, makes us juſt and righteous in the ſight of God. <hi>by this alone we are counted worthy of the Kingdome of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5. <hi>and accounted worthy to obtaine that world. and the reſurrection from the dead Luke</hi> 20.35. ſee 21.36. and ſaith <hi>Paul, David</hi> alſo deſcribeth the bleſſedneſſe of the man unto whom God imputeth righteouſneſſe without workes: and <hi>Abraham</hi> by the hand of Faith as an inſtrument, whereby he tooke faſt hold of the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt. giving glory to God, and ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered not through unbeleefe, it was counted, reckoned, or imputed unto him for righteouſneſſe; <hi>now it was not written for his ſake alone, that it was impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106746:4"/>unto him, but for us alſo, to whom it ſhall be imputed if we beleeve on him, who raiſed up Jeſus our Lord from the dead, Rom.</hi> 4.6 20, 21, 22, 23, 24. Thus we become righteous in the ſight of God, and although we were borne in the guilt of originall ſinne, yet now it is done away by Chriſt, <hi>for he hath laid on him the iniquity of us all, Iſa.</hi> 53.6. ſo then <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe iniquity is forgiven, and whoſe ſinne is covered;</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed is he to whom the Lord will not impute ſinne, Rom.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1. <hi>God was in Chriſt, reconciling the world to himſelfe, not imputing their trespaſſes,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. thus our ſinnes were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to Chriſt, but not infuſed into him, <hi>for ſtill he was the Lambe without blemiſh and without spot, who did no ſinne neither was guile found in his mouth,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.2.22.</p>
               <p>Yet he that knew no ſinne was made ſinne for us by imputation, they were accounted and reckoned to be his, <hi>and ſo Chriſt hath once ſuffered for ſinnes, the juſt for the unjuſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>That we might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. But this was not done by infuſing his righteouſneſſe into us to make us juſt, for we are ſinfull creatures, <hi>ſtill we are all as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing; and all our righteouſneſſe are as filthy ragges, Iſa.</hi> 64.6. So then we are juſtified by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt without us imputed or reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to be ours, for we are made the righteouſneſſe of God in him and not in our ſelves; this rightly obſerved might convince them of their proud boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, that they are as righteous as Chriſt, when as the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt that makes us juſt remaines in him and not in us.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we are ſaid <hi>to be justified by faith, Rom.</hi> 3.28.5.1. This is done when we take or receive the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, being purchaſed by the blood of Chriſt, and ſo imputed and reckoned to be ours, being reached forth unto us by the ſpirit of God and received by the hand of our faith, and ſo we come to have a true title to it; yet not by infuſion but by imputation and faith <hi>for as many as received him he gave power to become the ſonnes of God, even to them that beleeve on his Name, John</hi> 1.12. <hi>To him that worketh not, but beleveth on him, that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, Rom.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Not having mine owne righteouſneſſe which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe which is of God by faith, Phil.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Iſrael hath not attained to the law of righteouſneſſe: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, becauſe they ſought it not by faith but by the workes of the law; therefore they ſtumbled at that ſtumbling ſtone; but whoſoever beleeveth on him ſhall not be aſhamed, Rom.</hi> 9.31.32.33. Faith applying makes Chriſt ours, as <hi>Thomas</hi> beleeving ſaid, <hi>my God and my Lord, John</hi> 20.27, 28. Then I conclude this third cauſe of our juſtification being the inſtrumentall cauſe of it, with that ſaying of <hi>Paul, God justifies the circumciſion by faith, and uncircumciſion through faith; Rom.</hi> 3.30. but I never read of any that were juſtified without faith, or before faith or calling, let the Antenomeans prove the contrary if they can.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106746:4"/>
               <p>Fourthly, we are ſaid <hi>to be justified freely by his grace, Rom.</hi> 3.24. that is, when God the Father doth freely accept of the righteouſneſſe purchaſed by the blood of Chriſt, and accounts and imputes it unto us as ours, and reacheth it our unto us by his ſpirit, and we take and receive it by faith; thus to juſtifie us is freely of his grace; and this deſerves the title of free grace; <hi>For God ſo loved the World, that he gave his onely begotten ſonne, that whoſoever beleeveth in him ſhould not periſh but have everlasting life, John</hi> 3.16. <hi>He spared not his owne ſonne, but delivered him up for us all; how ſhall he not with him freely give us all things? Rom.</hi> 8.32. then is not this of free grace, <hi>and Chriſt gave his life a ranſome for all the Elect,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.6. <hi>he gave himſelfe for his Church,</hi> Ephe. 5.25. <hi>he gave his life a ranſome for many</hi> Matt. 20 28. <hi>he gave himſelfe for us to redeeme us from all iniquity, and to purifie unto himſelfe a peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, zealous of good workes,</hi> Titus 2.14. ſaith he, <hi>I lay downe my life, no man taketh it from me, I lay it downe of my ſelfe, I have power to lay it downe and I have power to take it up againe,</hi> John. 10.17.18. and then is not this out of free grace, <hi>and the ſpirit of God worketh where it listeth,</hi> John 3.8. then if the ſpirit of God reach out unto us the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, is it not of free grace, and out hand of faith by which we receive the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt? <hi>this faith is the gift of God</hi> Ephe. 2.8. then is not this alſo out of free grace: <hi>thus by grace ye are ſaved through faith, and that not of your ſelves, it is the gift of God,</hi> Ephe. 2.8. then let us ſpeake of this, <hi>to the praiſe of the glory of his grace wherein he hath made us accepted in the beloued,</hi> Ephe. 1.6.</p>
               <p>And thus farre of the cauſes of our juſtification in the ſight of God, being all that are mentioned in the Scripture except that of workes, which juſtifies our faith and perſons in the ſight of men, as <hi>James</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>James</hi> 2.24. but this we are not to ſpeake of at this time.</p>
               <p>From theſe caules we may eaſily ſee when we are juſtified in the ſight of God; I grant in the decree of God this righteouſneſſe of Chriſt was purchaſed vertually for all the Elect a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> well before his coming in the fleſh as afterward, <hi>for he was the Lambe ſlain from the foundation of the World,</hi> Rev. 13.8. Again, I grant that this purchaſe was actually paid above ſixteene hundred yeeres agon when Chriſt in our nature died actually and really on the Croſſe for beleevers; but to ſay that the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is really ours before that the ſpirit of God doth reach it forth unto us, <hi>or before we have any faith or calling;</hi> that is, before that we have either eye to ſee it, or hand of faith to receive and take it; this I ſay is a curſed error ſuggeſted by the father of lies, into thoſe that are led by him to beleeve lyes. For was that man in the Goſpell who had a legion of divels within him, juſtified when as the preſence of Chriſt was a torment to him, and he cryed out <hi>Jeſus thou ſonne of God moſt high, I beſeech thee tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment me not;</hi> I muſt needs confeſſe in one thing he was like our Antenomeans for no bonds could hold him: but when the divels were caſt out the man was in another mind, he that could not abide the preſence of Chriſt before, now
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106746:5"/>he can beſeech Chriſt that he might be with him, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.18.38.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall we be ſo fooliſh to thinke that the holy ſpirit of Chriſt will dwell in that foule and filthy heart, where the divell reignes and leads them captive at his will, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. but ſuch are all the Elect, before they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered out of the ſnare of the divell; ſhall we thinke that the holy ſpirit of Chriſt was in <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> when thoſe ſeven divels kept their randevouſe within her? What agreement hath Chriſt with the divell, that he ſhould be as an underling in that ſoule where the divell reignes? Doth Chriſt come to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie ſuch a ſoule, and not to ſanctifie it at the ſame time? Doth he not ſay <hi>come out of</hi> Babylon <hi>and be not partaker of her ſinnes, that ye receive not of her plagues,</hi> Rev. 18.4. <hi>Come out from among them and be ye ſeperate, ſaith the Lord, touch not the uncleane thing and I will receive you and I will dwell in you</hi> 2 Cor. 6.16, 17. <hi>but will Chriſt come into the ſtrong mans houſe and not bind him nor ſpoile his goods, is not Chriſt ſtronger then he?</hi> Luke 11.21, 22. Why then will Chriſt live in that ſoule that Sathan hath in poſſeſſion, it may be twenty or forty yeeres togther, before faith or effectuall calling be truely wrought in it? <hi>If ye be the Temple of God and his ſpirit dwell in you, if any man deſile the Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy—let no man deceive him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.16.17. Doth Chriſt ſay this, and will he himſelfe live and dwell among divels, eſpecially where they rule and reigne; I hope no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian truly juſtified will harbour ſuch blaſphemous thoughts within him, leſt they ſhould ſay, <hi>he hath an uncleane spirit,</hi> Marke 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</p>
               <p>Secondly, But will they yeeld and ſay, God forbid that we ſhould thinke that the holy Spirit of God ſhould dwell and live in that ſoul that the divell hath in poſſeſſion: then I reply and ſay, if any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is for the preſent none of his; <hi>Ye are not in the fleſh but on the ſpirit, if ſo be the Spirit of God dwell in you,</hi> Rom. 8.9. <hi>There ſhall no fleſh be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in his ſight,</hi> Rom. 3.20. but ſaith <hi>Paul. You in times paſted were Gentles in the fleſh, at that time yee were without Chriſt and without God in the world, but now in Chriſt Jeſus: yee who were ſometimes afarre off are made nigh by the blood of Chriſt,</hi> Ephe. 2.12.13. Then is the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt wrought in us by the Spirit of Chriſt, that makes us cleane temples for his Spirit to dwell in; and will not his holy Spirit live among divells in a cage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of uncleane and filthy luſts? and are they for the preſent without Chriſt and without God in the world, and in the fleſh? when as no fleſh living ſhall be juſtified in the fight of God; and having not the Spirit of God, they for the preſent are none of his: then how dare any man ſay <hi>that they are juſtified in the ſight of God, as ſoone as they had any being in this world?</hi> O horrible and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous doctrine! that makes the pure and holy Spirit of God, to be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, yea a very band to curſed divells, and filthy luſts elſe how can he live where the divells reigne: but thou O bleſſed Spirit of God, <hi>art of purer cyes then to behold evill; and canſt not look on iniquity with approbation,</hi> Hab. 1.13.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106746:5"/>
                  <hi>But ye in time paſt walked according to the courſe of the world, and according to the prince of the ayre that ruleth in the children of diſobedience</hi> ſaith Paul, <hi>wee all had our converſation in time paſt in the lusts of our fleſh, fulfilling the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the fleſh, and of the minde, and were by nature children of wrath even as others,</hi> Ephe. 3 2, 3. <hi>but were they juſtified as ſoone as they had any being,</hi> when they lived in all manner of ſinne whatſoever, the divell having their ſouls in full poſſeſſion, <hi>But ſuch were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed, but ye are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified,</hi> and then it follows, that they were <hi>juſtified,</hi> 1. Cor. 6.11. doth God charge us <hi>not to caſt pearls before ſwine, nor to give that which is holy to dogges;</hi> and will he give his chiefeſt benefits to them that remaine dogges and ſwine many yeers before they are effectually called, and have any true faith wrought in them; this is very pleaſing doctrine I muſt needs confeſſe for dogges and ſwine, but let the true Children of God take heed of it, leaſt they ſucke too much of their honey-combe, and ſo they poyſon their ſouls, and periſh eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally: but the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is received of us, by the hand of our faith, and ſo becomes ours, and you ſee that the Scripture is cleare for it. <hi>But they will needs be juſtified in the ſight of God without faith or calling;</hi> and I finde their reaſon to be this, becauſe that Chriſt took our nature upon him, and ſuffered in it, therefore by the humaine nature of Chriſt they are truly made the ſonnes of God by adoption, and juſtified without any faith or calling; they ſay that they need make no application of it to themſelves by faith, <hi>but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith it is unpoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> Heb. 11.6. <hi>and whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne,</hi> Rom. 14.23. therefore the truth is, <hi>as mary as received him, he gave power to become the Sonnes of God, even to them that beleeve on his name,</hi> John 1.12. God the Father ſigned and ſealed his Son to the office of Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip, but who hath any part in him: I anſ. <hi>He that receiveth his teſtimony hath ſet too his ſeal that God is true,</hi> John 3.35. <hi>He that beleeveth is not condemned, but he that beleeveth not is damned already, becauſe he hath not beleeved on the name of the onely begotten Sonne of God, he that beleeveth on the Sonne hath life, and he that beleeveth not the Sonne, ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him,</hi> John 3.18.36. <hi>He that beleeveth on the Sonne of God, hath the witneſſe in himſelfe, and he that beleeveth not God, hath made him a lyar, becauſe he beleeveth not the record that God gave of his Sonne,</hi> John 3.10.</p>
               <p>Then are ſuch as theſe unbeleevers uncalled, that make God a lyar, that are in a damnable eſtate, and the wrath of God abiding on them; are theſe <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the ſight of God?</hi> let ſuch doctrine be damned to the pit of hell; yet ſuch are the Elect as well as the Reprobate before their calling and converſion, as they came into the world untill they have juſtifying ſaith wrought in them, there was no difference betweene us and them, <hi>till our hearts were ſpirifiedly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aith,</hi> Rom. 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2.22. <hi>The Scripture hath concluded all under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he promiſe by faith in Jeſus Chriſt, may be given to them that beleeve,</hi> Gal. 3.22.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:106746:6"/>
               <p>But they ſay that faith is imperfect, therefore it cannot take hold ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on Chriſt to juſtifie them. I anſwer, if the begger can but reach out his hand, although it be weake or lame, to take his almes, yet it is his when he hath received it ſure enough, as if he had received it by a ſtronger hand, and it were folly to ſay that his almes is not his, becauſe his hand is weak or lame that received it: ſo he that by faith taketh the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, it is his ſure enough, although his faith were never ſo weak, if it be true faith, and it were folly to ſay that the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is none of his, becauſe he had not a ſtronger faith to receive it; but marke their folly, they ſay <hi>that a man may be juſtified without faith</hi> and yet not by faith becauſe it is too weak; but muſt we beleeve their errours, or the Spirit of God that cannot lye, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28.4.5.5.1. but they ſay faith will not endure for ever, therefore it cannot juſtifie us, as a hand or inſtrument.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, from the former ſimily, that when the begger hath received his almes, if he ſhould bethinke himſelfe then and ſay, this almes is not mine becauſe the hand that took it muſt periſh and rot in the grave; ſhould we not thinke it groſſe folly in him, and ſo to ſay that the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is not mine, becauſe my faith muſt end with my body; but if the beggers hand were afterward cut off, yet the almes is his for all that, and ſo let faith dye with us, yet having received the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, that is really ours to all eternity, and the Lord looks upon his people as they are cloathed with the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt being received by faith, and not ſo much upon the hand that received it, whether it be weak or ſtrong ſo it be in truth, and then he eſteemes us as perfectly juſtified, and ſhall abide ſo for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The next groſſe errours are theſe, they being juſtified aſſoone as they have any being, then God cannot ſee their ſinne, for they are perfectly righteous, even as righteous as Chriſt, aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one as they have any being; and faith doth but declare to them what was done before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſpeak of them that are elected before they have faith or calling, <hi>when thou waſt naked and bare, I ſaw thee polluted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n thine owne blood, then I looked upon thee,</hi> Eze. 16.6.8. ſhall we thinke that God did not ſee that catalogue of ſinnes in <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> before his converſion when as the pen-men of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wrote as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>The Lord turned not from the fierceneſſe of his wrath wherewith his anger was kindled againſt Iudah, becauſe of all the provocation that Manaſſeh had provoked him withall,</hi> 2 Kings 14.26. <hi>I will cauſe them to be removed into all kingdomes of the earth, becauſe of Manaſſeh,</hi> Jer. 15.4. then did not God ſee his ſinnes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though afterward he repented, and prayed, and the Lord was entreated of him 2. Chron. 33.13. and ſaith <hi>Peter, ye denied the Holy One and the Iust, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired a murtherer to be granted unto you, and killed the Prince of life,</hi> Acts 14.15.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106746:6"/>
                  <hi>Ieſus whom ye have crucified:</hi> now they were pricked at the heart, and three thouſand of them converted, Acts 2.36.37.41. then did <hi>Peter</hi> ſee their ſins, and did not God ſee them, when as he ſpake but as he was moved by the Holy Ghoſt; ſaith <hi>Paul, no theeves, nor covetous, nor drunkards ſhall inherite the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and ſuch were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed;</hi> doth <hi>Paul</hi> ſee them, and doth not the Spirit of God ſee them. <hi>In time past ye walked according to the courſe of the world, according to the prince of the power of the ayre that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the children of diſobedience, we all had our converſation in times paſt, in the luſts of our fleſh fulfilling the deſires of the fleſh, and were by nature children of wrath even as others.</hi> Ephe. 2.2, 3. did <hi>Paul</hi> ſee this, and did not God ſee it, at that time they were without Chriſt, and without God in the world, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. and did not God ſee them; ſaith <hi>Paul, I was before a blaſphomer and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuter, and injurious,</hi> 1. Tim. 1.13. did he ſee this and did not God ſee it? doth not Chriſt ſay, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me,</hi> I <hi>am Jeſus whom thou perſecuteſt,</hi> Acts 9.4.5. did not Chriſt then ſee his ſinne, although he was a choſen veſſell? <hi>ver.</hi> 15. but ſo much before ſaith or calling.</p>
               <p>But after converſion, did not God ſee <hi>Lots</hi> inceſt, and <hi>Noah</hi> drunke, and <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aarons</hi> unbeliefe, which barred them out of the land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> the Lord ſent <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>David</hi> to convince him of his ſinne, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. and he confeſſeth ſaying <hi>against thee onely have I ſinned, and done this evill in thy ſight,</hi> Pſal. 51.4. and ſaith <hi>Moſes thou haſt ſet our iniquities before thee, and our ſecret ſins in the light of thy countenance,</hi> Pſ. 90.8. &amp; ſaith the Lord) <hi>the high places were not taken away out of Iſrael; nevertheleſſe the heart of</hi> Aſa <hi>was perfect all his dayes</hi> 2. Chro. 15.17. <hi>yet he was wroth with him that told him of his ſinne, and put him in perſon and oppreſſed ſome of the people at the ſame time,</hi> chap. 16.10. <hi>and truſted in the Phyſician more then God</hi> ver. 12. then did not God ſee this, how ſhould the Prophet have known it if God had not told him? (ſaith the Lord) <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong my people are found wicked men they lay waite as he that ſetteth ſnares, they ſet a tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they catch men, they overpaſſe the deeds of the wicked they judge not the cauſe of the fatherleſſe, yet they proſper,</hi> Jer. 5.26.28. <hi>the ſinne of Iudah is written with a pen of Iron and with the point of a Diamond it is graven upon their heart.</hi> Jer. 17.1. (ſaith Paul) <hi>Peter and the other Jewes deſembled, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that Barnabas alſo was carried away with their diſſimulation,</hi> Gal. 2.13. Did <hi>Paul</hi> ſee this and did not God ſee it? when <hi>Peter</hi> denied Chriſt, did not he ſee him <hi>the Lord turned and looked upon him, and Peter remembred the words of the Lord, and Peter went out and wept bitterly,</hi> Luke 32.61.62. <hi>Yee fools, when will ye be wiſe, he that planted the care ſhall not he bear? and he that formed the eye ſhall not he ſee?</hi> Pſal. 94.8 9. the Lord knowes the thoughts of men; then I conclude, that a man may build upon the true foundation, hay, wood, or ſtubble, and he may ſuffer loſſe, but himſelfe ſhall be ſaved, yet ſo as by fire, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.12.15. therefore God ſees all the ſinnes of his juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed children, both before and after converſion.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:106746:7"/>
               <p>And although it be ſaid, <hi>He beheld no iniquity in</hi> Jacob, <hi>nor perverſneſſe in Iſrael, Num.</hi> 23.21. yet he ſaw it although he would paſſe by their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, <hi>Micah</hi> 7.18. and would not ſuffer <hi>Balaam</hi> to curſe them, neither would he forſake them, but correct them as he ſaw good and not according to their enemies rage which hath no mercy. And although it be ſaid that they cannot ſinne, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. yet ſaith the ſame <hi>Iohn, if we ſay that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves and the truth is not in us,</hi> 1 John 1.8. <hi>but yet they doe not ſinne that ſinne unto death,</hi> 1 John 5.16. neither with that whole ſwing as wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men doe: <hi>but the spirit ſtriveth againſt the fleſh, that they cannot doe the things that they would,</hi> Gal. 5.17. <hi>yet how can he be cleane that is borne of a woman? who can bring a cleane thing out of an uncleane?</hi> Job 14.1. <hi>how can man be justified with God, or how can he be cleane that is borne of a woman?</hi> Job 25.4. <hi>Who can ſay I have made my heart cleane,</hi> Pro. 20.7. <hi>there is no man living that ſinneth not,</hi> 1 Kings 8.46. 2 Chron. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. Eccle. 7.20. Then are we perfectly righteous; I meane in reſpect of degrees in this life; if this were ſo, how can there be any degrees of grace, as a ſtrong faith in ſome and a little faith in others? Or how can there be any groth in grace, if we had already attained, or were already perfect in degrees? but perfection in this world conſiſts not in the abſence of ſinne, but in the ſight of ſinne, and fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne, and groaning under the burthen of ſinne: and becauſe we ſinne daily, we muſt aske forgiveneſſe daily, and to be kept from temptation daily, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. we are not perfect in degrees of grace heere, therefore the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ordained to ſtrengthen our faith and to increaſe our holineſſe; but they that ſay that they are as perfect as Chriſt, what makes them to receive the Sacrament which is onely to ſtrengthen their faith? let the ſubtelleſt of them make anſwer if he can; but ſaith <hi>Paul, as ye abound in every thing, in faith, and utterance, and knowledge, and in all diligence, and in your love to us, ſo abound in this grace alſo,</hi> 2 Cor. 8.7. and ſaith <hi>Iohn, I pray God thou maieſt proſper even as thy ſoule prospereth,</hi> 3 John 2.</p>
               <p>Yet I grant that we are perfectly juſtified at once, but we are not perfectly ſanctified in this life, I meane in reſpect of degrees, although we be perfectly ſanctified in reſpect of parts, as a child hath all the parts of a man, but he muſt grow up unto the degrees of a man; then what bold preſumption is this, to ſay we are perfectly righteous as Chriſt, when as he neither wants parts nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; and beſides, it is in him as in the Fountaine, and in us but as the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne, <hi>out of his fulneſſe we receive grace for grace,</hi> John 1.17. againe, he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> never deſiled with ſinne as we are and we have no more of his righteouſneſſe then our weake faith is able to receive; yet I grant he that hath little ſhall have no lacke; yet there is degrees of grace here, and of glory hereafter; <hi>God gave not the spirit to Chriſt by meaſure.</hi> John 3.34. <hi>but unto every one of us is give grace according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt,</hi> Ephe. 4.7.16.13. the let us take heed leſt we offend Chriſt in boaſting of our righteouſneſſe, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:106746:7"/>we have nothing but what we have received, then why ſhould we boaſt as if we received it not, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.7. and take heed leſt you ſay God cannot ſee your ſin, <hi>for be ſure your ſinne will find you out,</hi> Num. 32.23. the Lord commended <hi>Iob for a perfect man,</hi> upright, <hi>and one that feared God and eſchewed evill,</hi> Job 1.1. yet <hi>Iob</hi> ſinned not onely in his paſſion, chap. 3. but afterward when he ſaith, <hi>the Lord breaketh me with a tempeſt, and multiplieth my wounds without cauſe,</hi> chap. 9.17. he ſaith, <hi>I am righteous, and God hath taken away my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, my wound is incurable without tranſgreſſion,</hi> chap. 34 5, 6. he ſaith <hi>I am cleane without tranſgreſſion, I am innocent, neither is there iniquity in me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold he findeth out occaſions againſt me,</hi> chap. 33.9, 10. he hath ſaid, <hi>I am more righteous then God,</hi> chap. 35.2. But did not God ſee all this? The Lord an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Iob</hi> and ſaid, ſhall he that contendeth with the Almighty inſtruct him, he that reproveth God let him anſwer it; wilt thou diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>null my judgement? wilt thou condemne me that thou maieſt be righteous? chap. 40.2.8. then how dare theſe men ſay, that they are as righteous as Chriſt, and that God can ſee no ſinne in them; but the truth is, they are ſicke of <hi>Iobs</hi> diſeaſe, and it were good for them if with him they would repent of their pride, <hi>and abhorre themſelves in duſt and aſhes,</hi> Job 42.6. then ſhould they ſee the end of the Lord, <hi>that the Lord is very pittifull and of tender mercy,</hi> James 5.11. but it may be they will catch at thoſe words, when the Lord ſaid to ſatan, <hi>thou mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt me againſt him to destroy him without cauſe.</hi> Job 2.3. I anſw. That the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell that accuſer of the brethren, could not tax him of any foule or ſcandelous ſinne, yet <hi>Iob</hi> had his failings as well as other men; as he ſaith, when his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is over <hi>that if he ſhould contend with God, he cannot anſwer one of a thouſand, then how ſhall man be juſt with God?</hi> Job 9.23. and ſaith <hi>David, O God thou knoweſt my fooliſhneſſe, and my ſinne is not hid from thee,</hi> Pſal. 69.5. <hi>Then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall I goe from thy preſence, thou knoweſt my down-ſitting and my up-riſing and underſtandeſt my thoughts a farre off, thou knoweſt my pathes, and art ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with all my wayes,</hi> Pſal. 139.2, 3. we heare of none that have learned the language of <hi>Canna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that pure language, <hi>that call on the name of the Lord and ſerve him with one conſent,</hi> Zeph. 3.9. in all the booke of God, ſaving, I am perfect, I am pure, I cannot ſinne if I would, or if I did, God cannot ſee my ſinne, I am as righteous as Chriſt, I need not grieve for my ſinne nor pray for pardon; but contrary ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> I am a ſinfull man O Lord; and ſaith <hi>Paul, I am the leaſt of all Saints</hi> Ephe. 3.8. <hi>and the chiefeſt of all ſinners,</hi> 1 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.15. and ſaith <hi>David pardon my ſin for it is great</hi> Pſal. 25.11. and in humility ſaith <hi>Abraham, I am but dust and aſhes;</hi> and ſaith <hi>Iacob, I am the least of all thy mercies;</hi> and ſaith <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt, <hi>I am not worthy to looſe the latchet of his ſhooe;</hi> and ſaith the Centurian, <hi>I am not worthy thou ſhouldest come under my Roofe;</hi> then where did theſe men learne this their proud boaſting of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, which the Lord ſaith <hi>is a stink in my wrath and a fire that burneth all the day,</hi> Iſa. 65.5.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106746:8"/>
               <p>In the next place, they tell us that they are aſſured of this their happy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition onely from a verball teſtimony, they ſay from the ſpirit of God; yet they deny the operation or ſanctifying worke of the ſame ſpirit of God to be any meanes whereby they may come to know their juſtification, for this they ſay is the doctrine of our legall teachers that goe by markes and ſignes.</p>
               <p>But here they deny one of the witneſſes, whereby we ſhould come to know our condition as we ſtand in the fight of God; for ſaith <hi>Paul, the ſpirit it ſelfe beareth witneſſe with our ſpirit that we are the ſonnes of God,</hi> Rom. 8.16. when Chriſt comes into the ſoule, he brings both water to ſanctifie and blood to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie us; <hi>This is he that came by water and blood, not by water onely, but by water and blood, then the ſpirit beareth witneſſe becauſe the ſpirit is truth; then the Father, the Word, and the Holy-ghost, will beare Record with our ſpirit here on earth, when our ſpirit with the witneſſe of water doth ſanctifie us, and that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther witneſſe from the blood of Chist doth justifie us, then are we really the ſons of God,</hi> 1 John 5.6, 7, 8. the ſpirit of God firſt convinceth the heart of ſinne, and then ſubjecteth the heart to his will, and then gives teſtimony by a divine reaſoning on this manner ſaying, He that beleeveth ſhall be ſaved; then cut ſpirit or conſcience makes anſwer, ſaying, I beleeve; then the concluſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from both theſe witneſſes, that I am the child of God.</p>
               <p>For it is not enough to have a perſwaſion that we are the children of God, except with that perſwaſion the gift of faith be wrought in us with all the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications of a child of God; as the grace of feare, not a ſlaviſh but a filiall feare, <hi>wrought in our hearts that we may not depart from him,</hi> Jer. 32.40. by neglecting of any duty commanded, or committing any ſinne forbidden, <hi>my ſonne feare thou the Lord</hi> Prov. 24.21, that is feare to offend him, <hi>and be carefull to pleaſe him in all things,</hi> John, 8.29. <hi>and to love and delight in his preſence,</hi> Pſal. 73.28. <hi>to honour and reverence his name,</hi> Mal. 1.6. Pſal. 111.9. <hi>and to ſerve and obey him in all things,</hi> John 5.30. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.39. he that findeth an inward deſire and an outward endeavour to doe theſe things is certainly the child of God; but a bare perſwaſion without any opperation or ſanctifying worke of the ſpirit of God in the ſoule, is the ſuggeſtion of the divell, <hi>who would perſwade them that kill you that they doe God ſervice,</hi> John 16.2. whoſe poſſeſſors ſlay them and hold themſelves not guilty, <hi>Zac.</hi> 11.5. The divell can eaſily turne himſelfe into an Angell of light, to deceive thoſe that deny all markes and ſignes of grace in them; but can the ſpirit of God come into the ſoule where the divell dwels in full poſſeſſion, and bind him and caſt him out, and change the will and affections from the ſervice of the divell to ſerve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? can the ſtrong holds of the divell be caſt downe, and the Throne of Chriſt ſet up without any noiſe or ſtirre in that ſoule? it is rather an evidence that ſoule was never changed, then not to be ſenceable of it any otherwayes but onely by a bare teſtimony, not looking what work the Lord hath wrought in it, nor knowing any thing by experience but by heare ſay, or a teſtimony of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106746:8"/>the divell, or ſome lying ſpirit which hath told him ſo.</p>
               <p>But what ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>John, Ye have an unction from the holy one, and ye know all things; the anointing which ye have received abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you but as the ſame anointing teacheth you of all things, and is truth and is no lye; and even as it hath taught you, ye ſhall abide in him; if ye know that he is righteous, ye know that every one that doeth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is borne of him,</hi> 1 John 2.20.27.29. ſometimes the ſpirit of God ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to give teſtimony a long time together; then our ſpirit or conſcience wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth from the worke wrought by the ſpirit of God, this anointing abideth in us, and teacheth when the verball voyce or teſtimony is gone or ceaſeth; for ſaith <hi>Paul, our rejoycing is the testimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, not with fleſhly wiſedome but by the grace of God, we have had our converſation in the world,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.12. <hi>I have lived in all good conſcience before God to this day.</hi> Act. 23.1. <hi>I ſay the truth in Chriſt I lye not, my conſcience bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me witnes in the Holy-ghoſt,</hi> Ro. 9.1. Thus you ſee that we muſt not content our ſelves with a bare teſtimony, but we muſt labour to ſee the work wrought in us, let but thy conſcience bring thee to thy tryall and thou ſhalt eaſily ſee how it is with thee; and doe not ſay that this is legall teaching, leſt thou be filled with fancies and no reall worke of grace be wrought as yet in thee, and doe not thinke that the ſpirit of God will worke when thou lieſt ſtill and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineſt an empty trunke or a dead ſtone; no thou muſt be made a living ſtone, and muſt worke actively by the movings of the ſpirit of God in thee: <hi>draw me, and we will runne after thee,</hi> Cant. 1.3. <hi>I ſhall runne the wayes of thy Commandements when thou doeſt inlarge my heart,</hi> Pſal. 119.32. but this they condemne as legall teaching, becauſe ſpirituall ſloathfulneſſe hath ſo poſſeſſed them, that they will make no other triall, but reſt upon a bare idle perſwaſion or teſtimony, but whether it came from God or the divell they know not.</p>
               <p>Well, they ſay they are juſtified as ſoone as they were borne, and then as righteous as Chriſt, and this they know from a bare teſtimony; <hi>now it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes ſay they, that God cannot correct them, neither doth he correct for their ſinne, but onely to exerciſe their faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I grant that God doth not puniſh his children in wrath and fury, with plagues and vengeance, but as gentle corrections from a loving father for their good, yet ſtill ſinne was the cauſe of it; ſaith <hi>David, there is no ſoundneſſe in my fleſh nor reſt in my bones, becauſe of my ſinne,</hi> Pſal. 38.3, 4, 5. <hi>why doth the living man complaine? man is puniſhed for his ſinne,</hi> Lam. 3.39. <hi>then art thou made whole, ſinne no more leſt a worſe thing come unto thee,</hi> John 5.14. if <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> a man after Gods owne heart ſinne ſcandalouſly, <hi>the ſword ſhall never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from his houſe,</hi> 2 Sam. 12 10. God is not partiall in his corrections, <hi>though</hi> Coniah <hi>were as the ſignet upon my right hand, yet would I plucks him thence,</hi> Ier. 22.24. <hi>that ſoule that ſinneth it ſhall dye,</hi> Ezek. 18. <hi>all things come alike to all; there is one event to the righteous and to the wicked,</hi> Eccleſ. 9.2. <hi>the wages
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106746:9"/>of ſinne is death,</hi> Rom. 6.23. And every ſickneſſe or inward grieſe or ſorrow or outward hurts, or maladies, all are but parts and parcels of this wages that we receive from the ſervice of ſinne, and we receive this wages by parts and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels daily; for as <hi>Adam</hi> in the day that he ſinned he began to dye, he received ſome part of that wages of ſinne, death ſeized upon him and ſlew him by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; and ſo we as ſoon as we were borne began to dye, and all thoſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſorrowes that doe befall us doe but hallen us to our end; but who is freed from theſe things? <hi>what man is he that liveth and ſhall not ſee death,</hi> Pſ. 89.41. <hi>our Prophets are dead, and our fathers are fallen aſleep; wiſe men dye as well as fooles, for all muſt dye, and be as water spile upon the ground</hi> 2 Sam. 14.14. then God doth correct and that heavily for ſinne; yet his corrections are ſweetned to his people, the ſting or bitterneſſe of them is tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n out; yet we ſhall not be freed from corrections nor death, ſo long as we carry a body of ſinne daily about with us; <hi>death is paſſed upon all men; for that all have ſinned</hi> Rom. 5.12. but will they ſay that death is not a correction? <hi>it is the king of terrours,</hi> Iob 18.14. will they ſay death is but to exerciſe their faith; but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe one of them were ſhot with a bullet, how would he exerciſe his faith? or can they exerciſe their faith to prevent a ſinne, when they are corrected for their ſinne already committed; ſaith <hi>David, before J was afflicted J went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray,</hi> Pſal. 119.67. and <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> was converted in the furnace of afflictions, which was the meanes to beget his faith, and not to exerciſe it before he had it: it is manifeſt enough that God doth correct his people for ſinne; <hi>if thy children forſake my law, and if they breake my ſtatutes, then J will viſit their tranſgreſſions with a rod and their iniquity with ſtripes; nevertheleſſe J will not take away my mercy from him.</hi> Pſal. 89.30. then let not the Antonomeans forſake Gods law, leſt they feele the weight of his correcting hand, <hi>you have</hi> I <hi>knowne of all the families of the earth, therefore</hi> I <hi>will puniſh you for your iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> Amos 3.2. then let them take heed how they ſay when they ſinne, tuſh, God ſees not, God is not like to themſelves; <hi>he will reprove them, and ſet their ſinnes in order before them, conſider th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ye that forget God leſt he teare you in <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eces and there be none to deliver you</hi> Pſal. 50.21. <hi>God will correct</hi> Jacob <hi>in meaſure, and will not leave him altogethen unpuniſhed,</hi> Jer. 10.24.20.11. <hi>for the tranſgreſſion of Jacob is all this,</hi> Micah 1.5. <hi>Zachariah</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> are as famous as any in all the Scripture, for being both juſt and righteous before God and walking in all the Commandements and Ordinances of the Lord blameleſſe; yet ſaith the Angell to him <hi>thou ſhalt be dumb and not able to speake</hi> (which was a ſore correction) <hi>becauſe thou beleeveſt not my words,</hi> Luke 1.6.20. and <hi>Jehoſaohat</hi> was a good man, yet if he helpe the ungodly and love them that hate the Lord; there ſhall wrath from the Lord be upon him, nevertheles there are good things found in him, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 19.23. &amp; <hi>Miriam</hi> was a good woman yet if ſhe ſpeake againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> the anger of the Lord is kindled, <hi>and behold</hi> Miriam <hi>became leprous white as ſnow,</hi> Num. 12.1.9, 10. <hi>for whom the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106746:9"/>Lord loveth he chasteneth, and ſcourgeth every ſonne that he receiveth; if ye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dnre chastening whereof all are partakers, then are ye ſonnes and not baſtards,</hi> Heb. 12.6, 7, 8. <hi>Ephraim</hi> bemoaned himſelfe thus, <hi>Thou haſt chaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſed me;</hi> yet ſaith the Lord, <hi>Ephraim is my deare ſonne, he is a pleaſant child,</hi> I <hi>doe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly remember him ſtill, my bowels are troubled for him,</hi> I <hi>will ſurely have mercy on him,</hi> ſaith the Lord, Jer. 31.18.20. it is a ſigne of a humble heart, when the Land is ſcourged for ſinne, to acknowledge our ſinnes to be the cauſe of it, as <hi>David</hi> did, ſaying to the Lord, I <hi>even</hi> I <hi>onely have ſinned and done evill indeed, but as for theſe ſheep what have they done?</hi> 1 Chron. 21.17. ſee 2 Sam. 24.10. Againe, when <hi>Nathan</hi> came to him, he ſaid, I <hi>have ſinned against the Lord,</hi> 2 Sam. 12.13. Againe, it is the brand of a reprobate, when God cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to correct him for his ſinne, I <hi>will no more puniſh your daughters when they commit whoredome, nor your spouſes when they commit adultery:</hi> Ephraim <hi>is joyned to Idols, let him alone.</hi> Hoſea 4.14.17. ſo when the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d ſmote <hi>Uzzah</hi> for his errour that he dyed, <hi>David</hi> was afraid of the Lord t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t day, 2 Sam. 6.7.8. when Chriſt ſaid to his Apoſtles, one of you ſhall betray me, every one ſuſpected his owne heart ſaying, Lord is it I, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. then let not us ſay, God cannot correct us, nor any other for our ſinnes; which is one maine cauſe why they refuſe the covenant; but let them know if God have forgiven them, yet he will take vengeance on their inventions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99.8. then if God ſend <hi>Jonah</hi> to cry againſt the wickedneſſe of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> and he goe to <hi>Tarſheſh</hi> from the preſence of the Lord, God will ſend a great and mighty wind and tempeſt, ſo that the ſhip was like to be broken, and <hi>Jonah</hi> forced to confeſſe and ſay, <hi>for my ſake this great tempeſt is come upon you,</hi> Ionah 1.2.12. <hi>the judge of all the earth will doe right,</hi> Gen. 18. <hi>and ye ſhall know that</hi> I <hi>have not done without cauſe all that</hi> I <hi>have done, ſaith the Lord God,</hi> Ezek. 14.23. and when ſome received the Sacrament unworthily, <hi>for this cauſe many were ſicke and weake and many dead,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. then doth not God correct his people for ſinne, or will they ſay they dye onely for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ryall, for theſe men were ſome of them Gods people which ſhall not be condemned with the world, ver. 32. <hi>judgement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth at the houſe of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.17. which makes <hi>David</hi> ſay, <hi>my fleſh trembleth for feare of thee, and</hi> I <hi>am afraid of thy judgements,</hi> Pſal. 119.120. Hab. 3.15. but theſe people are ſo full of mirth from thoſe following grounds, that they brake out into laughter ſaying, they cannot ſinne being in Chriſt, and if they ſhould yet God cannot ſee it, or if he ſhould chance to ſee it, he cannot be diſpleaſed with it or if he ſhould be diſplea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, his hands are bound that he cannot correct them for it; then they muſt neither repent, nor be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor pray for the pardon of any ſinne, neither paſt, preſent, nor to come; neither muſt they heare of their ſinnes any more; this fils their faces full of comfort, when their hearts have cauſe enough to be heavy; ſaith <hi>Salomon, he is the happy man that feareth alwayes.</hi> Prov. 28.14. when this feare ſtirres up watchfulneſſe and diligence, <hi>to pleaſe God with reverence and godly feare,</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106746:10"/>12.28, a child may feare his fathers rod, although he feare not to be diſinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>even the reghteous ſhall ſee and feare,</hi> Pſal 52.6. legall threatnings cannot hurt the righteous; ſaith <hi>David, let the righteous ſmite me it ſhall be a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and let him reprove me, it ſhall be an excellent oyle which ſhall not breake mine head,</hi> Pſal. 141.6. theſe lower hearbs will make us reliſh promiſes the better, and ſtick faſter to them and it will inflame our love to God more deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for ſaving us from thoſe dangers threatned, and it will ſtirre up compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in us towards our brethren, to helpe them out of thoſe dangers, and to worke out our owne ſalvation with feare and trembling, Phil. 2.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus they being justified as ſoone as they are borne, and then as righteous as Chriſt; this they know from a bare teſtimony, or revelation, or ſuggeeſtion, then God cannot correct nor puniſh them for ſin: now it followes, that they are freed from the commanding power of the law of God, by their free grace they are diſcharged from all duty or obedience to it, now the law of God is no rule for them, but wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> they doe is onely out of love and curteſie, for they owe God nothing at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here I grant that the Juditiall law was not made for us, and the ceremoniall law was ended in Chriſt, but the morrall law abides for ever; I meane the commanding and diſcovering power of it remaines as a glaſſe to beleevers, and as a rule or a bridle to keep them in continuall obedience to the Lord.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid, <hi>If ye be led by the Spirit, ye are not vnder the law, but under grace,</hi> Gal. 5.18. it is to be underſtood, you do obey the law freely without the laſhing or conſtraining power of the law, and where it is ſaid, <hi>ſin ſhall not have dominion over you, for you are not under the law, but under grace,</hi> Rom. 3.13. this is plain, that if ſinne have dominion over you, you are under the curſe and condemning power of the law; but from the raigne of ſinne and from the curſe of the law, you are freed by Chriſt, Rom. 8.1. Gal. 3.13, This curſe and condemning power of the law, is not made for a righteous man but for the ungodly, for ſinners, and unholy, for murtherers, and whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, theeves, and lyars, and perjured perſons, or any other ſinne that is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſound doctrine, 1. Tim. 1.9.10. <hi>Wherefore the law is holy, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement holy, just, and good,</hi> Rom. 7.12. but they will have the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power of the law, to laſt but till <hi>John</hi> the Batpiſt, becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>the law and the Prophets were untill John.</hi> Luke 16.16. and the law <hi>was added for tranſgreſſors till the ſeed ſhould come,</hi> Gal. 3.19. I anſwer, <hi>they propheſied of Chriſt till John,</hi> Mat. 11.13. but when <hi>John</hi> ſhewed them the Meſſiah, and poynted to him with his finger, ſaying, <hi>Behold the Lambe of God that taketh away the ſinnes of the world, John</hi> 1.29. then they ceaſed to propheſie, or to foretell of his coming when they ſaw him; but to ſay that the law ſhould la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> but till <hi>John</hi> is yet to prove, and cannot be gathered from this place; <hi>For til<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the law, ſinne was in the world,</hi> Rom. 5.13. but will they gather from hence that there was no ſinne in the world after that the law was given; if <hi>Mical</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106746:10"/>be childleſſe till her death, ſhe muſt needs be ſo for ever; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to <hi>Timothie, Till I come give attendance to reading, exhortation, and doctrine, neglect not the gift that is in thee,</hi> 1. Tim. 4.13.14. but after that <hi>Paul</hi> is come, muſt he neglect theſe duties, becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>do them till</hi> I <hi>come;</hi> thus they force the Scriptures to favour their errours. Then they ſay <hi>Chriſt is the end of the law for righteouſneſſe,</hi> ſo I ſay too, for he hath put an end to all types and ſhadowes of the Ceremoniall law, and he hath put an end to the curſe and bondage of the morall law; <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed us from the curſe of the law, being made a curſe for us,</hi> Gal. 3.13. <hi>and from the condemning power of it,</hi> Rom. 8.1. but if we ſpeak of obedience to the commanding power of the law, Chriſt is the ſcop and end to which all our obedience tends, and he is the end for whoſe ſake all the promiſes are made good unto us, and not for our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and he alone gives being and performance to them all, 2 Cor. 1.20. and he is the end of the law for righteouſneſſe, that is, the law brings us to Chriſt for righteouſneſſe, and in him we have righteouſneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fulfil the laws, not inherent but by imputation? Then are we freed from the law, no, then are we tyed faſter in obedience to it, foraſmuch as we had no power before to do it, but now through Chriſt we can doe all things. Againe, they ſay they have the ſpirit of God for their rule, and they doe all by a free ſpirit, and need not the law to rule them; for they are like unto trees that bring forth fruit of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves without any teaching. But let them know that trees although they were never ſo rooted in the earth, yet they would never bring forth fruit of themſelves, but by the meanes of outward helps, as the Sunne and the raine and other helpes, and beſides, the ſpirit of God brings them to the rule of the law, to ſquare and try all their actions by it, and ſhewes us wherein we faile, and when we doe that which is required of us.</p>
               <p>But ſure theſe men thinke that our Fathers went to Heaven by one meanes, and we muſt goe thither by another meanes; but ſaith the Apoſtle, we write unto you no new commandement but the old, which ye have had from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, then there is but one way, <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.39. for them and us; had they the law? ſo have we; and if we have the Goſpell, ſo had they, and the law and the goſpell command the ſame vertues, and both forbid the ſame vices: then what a curſed errour is this to thinke that God the ſonne ſhould free beleevers from all obedience to God the Father; but we know that he who honours the ſon muſt needs honour the Father, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.23. the ſonne ſpeakes not of himſelfe but from the Father, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. <hi>then he that ſaith he abideth in him, ought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alſo to walke even as he walked,</hi> 1 John 2.6. but how was that ſaith he, <hi>Loe I come! in the volume of thy booke it is written of me to doe thy will O God: then ſaid I, loe!</hi> I <hi>come to doe thy will O God;</hi> Heb. 10.7.9. and ſaith he, <hi>I ſeeke not mine owne will, but the will of the Father that ſent me,</hi> John 5.30. Mat. 26.39. <hi>my doctrine is not mine, but his that ſent me,</hi> Iohn 7.16. <hi>he was ſubject to his Parents,</hi> Luke 2.51. and ſaith <hi>Paul, let the ſame mind be in you
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106746:11"/>that was in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Phil. 2.5. and Chriſt ſaith, <hi>learne of me,</hi> Mat. 11.29. I <hi>have given you an example that ye ſhould doe as</hi> I <hi>have done to you; if ye know theſe things, happy are ye if ye do them,</hi> Ioh. 13.15.17. <hi>and for ſuffering</hi> he left us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. then did Chriſt free us from the law, or did he not rather by his own example ſhew us how to obey the law more exactly, and ſaith <hi>David, thy law endures for ever in heaven,</hi> Pſa. 119.89. <hi>and the Angels do the commandments of God, and hearken to the voice of his word</hi> Pſal. 10.3. and do not the Saints liev there by the ſame rule, have they not all one charter, why doth Chriſt teach us to pray, <hi>that we may doe the will of God on earth as it is done in heaven, Mat.</hi> 6. are we on earth more perfect then they, or more ſanctified then they, or hath Chriſt done more for us then for them? if not, why then ſhould we forſake that rule that muſt be for Saints and Angels for ever? they boaſt of their <hi>juſtification,</hi> but ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi> how can they be juſtified that are not friends with the law of God? and <hi>Luther</hi> whom they chall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nge for their own friend he rangeth them among the unjuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and by his c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſure rejects them among the unregenerate; for ſaith he, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>I delight in the law of God, in the inward man, and I ſerve the law of God in my mind,</hi> Rom. 7.22.25. and ſaith <hi>David, O how I love thy law!</hi> Pſal. 119.97. <hi>and the bleſſed man delights in the law of the Lord, and in his law doth he meditate day and night,</hi> Pſal. 1.2. then were Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and the faithfull Miniſters that ſucceed them all legall Preachers, for urging the law and preſſing on beleevers the obedience of the law; yea; to the law more ſtrictly, expounded by Chriſt, as you ſhall ſee anon, then it was by the Scribes and Phariſees. <hi>Then he that neglects the Commandements and ſhall teach men ſo, ſhall, be leaſt in the Kingdome of Heaven; but he that doeth them and teacheth men ſo, ſhall be called great in the Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> Mat. 5.19. againe, how can a man teach obedience of faith, but he muſt needs teach obedience to the law, <hi>for if faith beare no fruits it is a dead faith,</hi> James 2.17, 18. and if thoſe workes or fruits be not regulated by the law, <hi>they are but grapes of gall which growes on the vine of</hi> Sodom, <hi>and their clusters are bitter</hi> Deut. 32.32. the workes of the law and the workes of faith are the ſame thing, they may be diſtinguiſhed but not devided; and ſaith Chriſt to the Lawyer, <hi>what is written in the law? how readeſt thou? and he anſwered, thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule; and with all thy ſtrength, and thy neighbour as thy ſelfe; and Chriſt ſaid unto him, thou haſt anſwered right, this doe and thou ſhalt live,</hi> Luke 10.26, 27, 28. and doth not faith worke by love? Gal. 5.6. againe, how can a man beleeve that God will ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to thouſands of them that love him and keepe his commandements, Exod. 20.6. when they ſhew no endeavour at all to keepe or obey them, but ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully terme them legall teachers that call for any obedience from them; but what makes them to love God, if the commanding power of his law doth not? or if they yeeld to this command of the law, why not as well to another? b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106746:11"/>if they love God, and not as a duty to his law that commands it, it is bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, groundleſſe, and in the end will be comfortleſſe; and why doe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in Chriſt but to fulfill the Fathers commandement? for this is his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, <hi>that we ſhould beleeve on the name of his ſonne Jeſus Chriſt, and love one another as he the father gave us commandement,</hi> 1 Iohn 3.23. <hi>this is the vvorke of God to beleeve on him vvhom he hath ſent.</hi> Iohn 6.29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then doe we make void the law through faith, God forbid; y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a we eſtabliſh the law</hi> Rom. 3.31. <hi>being not without th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> law to God, but under the law to Chriſt</hi> 1 Cor. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. <hi>He that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable to God and approved of men,</hi> Rom. 14.18. <hi>He th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſpeaketh evill of his brother and judgeth his brother, ſpeaketh evill of the law and judgeth the law, but if thou judge the law, thou art not a doer of the law but a judge,</hi> Jam. 4.11. <hi>If ye have reſpect to perſons ye commit ſinne, and are convinced of the law as tranſgreſſors; whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall keep the whole law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all; for he that ſaid thou ſhalt not commit adultery, ſaid alſo thou ſhalt not kill; now if thou doe not commit adultery, yet if thou kill thou art a tranſgreſſour of the law,</hi> Jam. 2.9.10.11. <hi>Then bear one anothers burden, and ſo fulfill the law of Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 6.2, here Chriſt claimes the law to be his, <hi>There is one lawgiver, who is able to ſave and to deſtroy,</hi> Iam. 4.12. the Prophets came all ſaying, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord;</hi> but when Chriſt came and cleered the law from thoſe falſe gloſſes of the Scribes and Phariſees, which ſay, <hi>thou ſhalt not kill;</hi> but I ſay <hi>whoſoever is angry vvith his brother without a cauſe, is in danger of judgement.</hi> Mat. 5. and ye have heard ſay, <hi>thou ſhalt not commit adultery;</hi> but I ſay, whoſoever looketh on a woman to luſt after her hath committed adultery already in his heart, and ſo of the reſt; therefore obey it and ſo fulfill the law of Chriſt; for he ſaith <hi>I am not come to destroy the law till Heaven and earth paſſe away, not one tittle or jot ſhall in no wiſe paſſe from the law,</hi> Mat. 5.17.18. now when Chriſt hath claimed the law to be his, and cleered it from their falſe gloſſes, then there comes a young man to him ſaying, <hi>Master, what good thing ſhall I doe to inherite eternall life?</hi> then Chriſt anſwers him directly ſaying <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f thou wilt enter into life keepe the Commandements;</hi> he ſaith unto him, <hi>which?</hi> Chriſt anſwered him, <hi>thou ſhalt not commit adultery, nor murther, nor ſteale, nor beare falſe witneſſe, honour thy father and mother, and love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe,</hi> Mat. 19.16, 17. and although outwardly he had beene doing ſomething for which Chriſt loved him, yet there was that inward luſt of covetouſneſſe ſtucke faſt in his heart; therefore Chriſt ſends him backe to the law to be humbled for it, <hi>this one thing thou lackeſt,</hi> Marke 10.21. before thou art fit for faith or to have treaſure in heaven, goe to the law and ſee thy ſinne, for by the law is the knowledge of ſinne, Rom. 3.20. then is the law ſinne <hi>nay I had not known ſinne but by the law, I had not knowne luſt except the law had ſaid, thou ſhalt not luſt,</hi> Rom. 7.7. and the law ſhewes us our failings when we are in the ſtate of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106746:12"/>grace, for it we ſhould caſt off the law from being a rule to us, we ſhould nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know when we ſin nor how to recover our ſelves, <hi>for where no law is there is no tranſgreſſion,</hi> Rom. 4.15. <hi>for whoſoever ſinneth tranſgreſſeth the law, for ſinne is the tranſgreſſion of the law,</hi> 1 Ioh. 3.4. <hi>then it is time Lord to worke, when they have made voyd thy law,</hi> Pſal. 119.126. <hi>rivers of teares runne downe mine eyes becauſe they keepe not thy law,</hi> ver. 136. ſo then they that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God, for the carnall mind is enmity againſt God, <hi>it is not ſubject the law of God, neither indeed can be,</hi> Rom. 8.7.</p>
               <p>Then what ſhall we ſay to thoſe ſonnes of <hi>Beliall,</hi> that are ſo weary of the law, that as much as in them lyes they ſeeke to make it void, both in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding duties and forbidding of vices, but curſed be ſuch tenets; hath the divell ſo prevailed with them as to make them take counſell againſt the Lord and againſt his Anointed, ſaying, <hi>let us breake their cords and caſt away their bonds from us,</hi> Pſal. 2.2, 3.</p>
               <p>How dare they ſay, that Chriſt hath freed them from all duty, and that they owe the Lord no obedience at all, ſo that what they doe is out of their free love and curteſie, and not from any duty or obedience to his law, which is no rule for beleevers: But doe they make void the law, God forbid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. faith ſhould be imployed to fetch power from Chriſt to enable us to obey the law, <hi>vve are not ſufficient of our ſelves to thinke any thing as of our ſelves, but our ſufficiency is of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.5. <hi>but vve can doe all things through Chriſt ſtrengthening us,</hi> Phil. 4.13. then faith doth not free us of our duty, but makes us more able to performe our duty to the law of God, and therefore it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the obedience of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. it ſtands not with true faith, to call them legall divines by way of ſcorne and diriſion, that call upon us and put us in mind of our duty to the Lord, becauſe ſay they, we owe him none; but let them know and be ſure that their ſinnes will find them out, <hi>Numb.</hi> 32.23. let them take heed how they ſay that God is like to themſelves, leſt he reprove them and ſet their ſinnes in order before them; <hi>now conſider this ye that forget God leſt he teare you in peeces, and there be none to deliver you,</hi> Pſal. 50.21.22. cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly that man was never juſtified from his ſinne, that thinkes it not his duty to mortifie it, and doth not grieve and mourne for want of ſtrength to ſubdue it, and his duty to pray againſt it, which our Antinomeans renounce, ſaying, this is legall teaching, and they will try their condition, onely from a bare te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony as I ſaid before; although it be a ſuggeſtion of the divell, it may ſerve their turne well enough, while they deſpiſe the operation of the ſpirit of God ſanctifying and changing them, and ſetting up his owne Image in them, giving them grace for grace with Chriſt; they ſay if we looke upon theſe markes and ſignes to know our condition, this is legall; this vvill not ſtand with their free grace, vvhich frees them of that labour vvhich ſhould ſearch and try them, they take all from a teſtimony vvithout examination; but this build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vvill not endure the ſtorme of perſecution.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106746:12"/>
               <p>Then they ſay that they love God terribly, and this frees them from their duty: they ſay, the love of Chriſt conſtraines them, but they vvill not tell us to what, for they flatly deny all duty to the Law of God: but ſaith Chriſt, when ye have done all that ye can you have but done your duty, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.10. and ſaith Chriſt, ye call me Lord and Maſter, and ye ſay well, for ſo I am, but then ye ought to waſh one anothers feet, for the ſervant is not above the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: <hi>if ye knovv theſe things, happy are ye if ye doe them, John</hi> 13.15.16. if the yong man call him Maſter, preſently he ſends him to his worke and duty of obedience, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.17. <hi>if I be your Maſter vvhere is my feare? Mat.</hi> 1.6. It is not enough to call him Lord and Maſter, and then to deny all duty of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him; this was the love of <hi>Judas</hi> who cryed, <hi>Hale Maſter,</hi> when he betrayed him: ſo theſe men ſay that they love him dearely, but they defie all duty to him, for they owe him none; but time will come when they that ſay Lord, Lord, ſhall not come to heaven, but <hi>he that doth the vvill of my Father which is in heaven, Mat.</hi> 7.21. But their true love frees them from all duty: but what love they have I know not, for this is the law of God, that we keepe his Commandements, and his Commandements are not grievous, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.3. But if they love God, why doe they deſpiſe his Law, which ſaith <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule, and with all thy might: theſe words I command thee this day, Deut.</hi> 6.5.6. and where is their love to Chriſt they boaſt ſo much of; for he ſaith theſe words in anſwer to the Lawyer, <hi>This is the firſt and great Commandement in the Law, to love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and vvith all thy ſoule and vvith all thy mind, and the ſecond is like unto it, thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe, on theſe tvvo Commandements hang all the Lavv and the Prophets, Mat.</hi> 22.37.38. And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake the ſame words of the ſecond Table, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe Levit.</hi> 19.18. ſo that you ſee the ſweet harmony between Chriſt and <hi>Moſes;</hi> and the ſame was with <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith, Thou ſhalt not commit adultery, kill nor ſteale, nor beare falſe witneſſe, nor covet: love worketh no ill to his neighbour, therefore love is the fulfilling of the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.9, 10. then doth love drive them from the law: ſaith <hi>David, Oh hovv I love thy lavv;</hi> and what followes? <hi>it is my meditation all the day, Pſal.</hi> 119.97. thy teſtimonies are my delight, and what followes? and my councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. Unleſſe thy law had beene my delight, I had periſhed in mine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction: I will never forget thy precepts, for with them thou haſt quickned me <hi>ver.</hi> 92.93. tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is, the ſhewing him his duty revived his dull ſpirits that began to flagge and faint: but theſe men deſpiſe the Law of God, becauſe it is ſent by <hi>Moſes;</hi> but ſaith Chriſt, had ye beleeved <hi>Moſes,</hi> ye would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved me, for he wrote of me; and if ye will not beleeve his writings, how ſhall ye beleeve my words, <hi>John</hi> 5.46.47. <hi>Moſes</hi> told them that the ſeed of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he woman ſhould breake the ſerpents head, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15, and that the Lord thy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106746:13"/>God will raiſe up unto thee a Prophet from the middeſt of thee of thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren like unto me; unto him ſhall ye hearken, and he ſhall ſpeake unto them all that I command him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.18. and ſaith the Lord, This is my beloved Sonne, heare him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5. the Apoſtle to ſet forth the faithfulneſſe of Chriſt, compares him with faithfull <hi>Moſes;</hi> for ſaith he, Chriſt was faithfull to him that appointed him; as alſo <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithfull in all his houſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.2. then why muſt <hi>Moſes</hi> be ſo deſpiſed, who was as faithfull to the Lord as ever man was, but yet the meſſage was the Lords? then why muſt Gods law be deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? becauſe you like not the meſſenger that brings it. Againe, Chriſt cleares the law of <hi>Moſes</hi> from their falſe gloſſes: but it ſeemes in their conceit that <hi>Moſes</hi> hath ſo defiled it, that Chriſt is not able to cleare it againe except he take it quite away; for they are not minded to make it a rule to beleevers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they periſh by ſwarving from it; as that curſed Whoremonger that is ſo buſie to broach thoſe ſweet tolerations for his owne vilany, and for ſuch as he, vvho eſteeme the law of God as a heavy burden to them, and as a bridle to reſtraine them from their ſweet pleaſures in ſinne, but if they leave this rule, they muſt needs offer polluted bread to the Lord, and the blind and the lame. and the ſick, in their offering, vvhich is evill; that their governour vvould not be pleaſed vvith nor accept their perſons then curſed be that deceiver that hath in his flocke a male and offereth unto the Lord a corrupt thing, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.7 8 9, 14. if the Lord vvrite unto you the great things of his law and you count them as a ſtrange thing <hi>Hoſea</hi> 8.12. If you doe not make the law of God your guide you muſt needs bring ſtrange fire to the Lord, as the Sonnes of <hi>Aaron</hi> did and periſhed for their preſumption, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.12. for vvho required theſe things at your hands, to tread my Courts? to vvhat purpoſe is all that ye doe? bring no more vaine oblations, it is iniquity, my ſoule hateth them, they are a trouble to me, I cannot beare them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.11.12.13.14. ſee <hi>Amos</hi> 5.25.26. He that kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth an oxe is as if he ſlew a man and he that ſacrificeth a lambe as if he cut off a dogges necke; he that offereth an oblation as if he offered ſwines blood; and he that burneth Incenſe as if he bleſſed an Idoll; the reaſon is becauſe they have choſen their owne vvayes <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.3. thus ſaith the Lord ſtand in the vvay and ſee, aske for the old pathes vvhere is the good vvay, and vvalke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and ye ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules; but they laid vve vvill not vvalke therein: Heare O earth I vvill bring evill upon this people, the fruit of their owne thoughts, becauſe they have not harkened to my law but rejected it, then it followes, to vvhat purpoſe cometh their incenſe to me from, <hi>Sheba,</hi> your offerings are not acceptable, nor your ſacrifices ſweet unto me <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16.19.20. theſe people are like unto King <hi>Saul,</hi> vvho for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooke the commandement of the Lord and then vvould goe offer the ſacrifice of his owne deviſing; but to obey had beene better then ſacrifice, and to harken then the fat of Rams, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22. ſo theſe men forſake the law of God, and ſay that it is no rule
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106746:13"/>for beleevers; and then they ſay that love will move them to ſomething unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, not as any duty nor done in obedience to the Lord, but out of free love and meere good will and curtiſie; but I ſay, if it be not done by the rule, and weighed in the ballance of the Sanctuary, but onely of their owne head, God will ſay of them as he ſaid of <hi>Saul, Rebellion is as the ſinne of witchcraft, and ſtubbornneſſe is as iniquity and idolatry, becauſe thou haſt rejected the word of the Lord, he alſo hath rejected thee from being King,</hi> 1 Sam. 15.23. and now O Iſrael, what doth the Lord require of thee, but to feare the Lord thy God, and to walke in all his wayes, and to love him, and to ſerve him with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule and to keep the Commandements of the Lord and his ſtatutes, which I command thee this day for thy good? <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12, 13. but they will anſwer that their free grace hath freed them from all duties, ſo that they doe not ſtand in feare to oftend the Lord, neither are they bound to walke in all his wayes nor to ſerve the Lord with all their heart and ſoule, nor to endeavour to keep his lawes and ſtatutes for their good, this they ſay is le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, and but the words of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and they can love God; and this they can ſhew ſufficiently from their free will unrequired of God, or done in obedience to his law, for it is no rule for them, neither doe they acknowledge any duty to it. Againe they are not acquainted with the graces of Gods ſpirit that are wrought in his people; I meane ſuch as theſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. tell them what carefulneſſe godly ſorrow hath wrought in you, and they will anſwer, that their care is taken; and what a cleering of your ſelves, and they will ſay that they are as cleere from ſinne as Chriſt; and of anger for ſinne, and they will ſay, that they have none to be angry at; and of feare to offend God, and they will ſay, that they cannot ſinne to offend him; tell them of a deſire to pleaſe God, and they will ſay, that Chriſt hath done that already and what need they to trouble themſelves; tell them of a zeale for Gods glory and revenge on ſinne, and they will ſay, theſe are legall things which they are freed from, and ſo of all other graces they know not what we meane: But they have faith to ſee that all is done by Chriſt without faith or application, onely when faith is come by it, they can ſee what was done in them before and without it; they ſay Chriſt lives in them, and acts and moves them as we move a ſtone; and they are ſtill as an empty trunke for his ſpirit to move in, ſo that nothing is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them, but onely to let the ſpirit of God-doe his owne vvorke in them and by them; &amp; they remaine ſtill but dead ſtones; they are not acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with that principle of life that is put into Gods people; they are not as yet made living ſtones, but they like <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe remaine as they were, a though ſhee ſpeake with mans voyce yet an Aſſe ſtill, and ſo are they; but the child of God is quickned that vvas dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.1. ſaith Chriſt, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he that heareth my word and beleeveth on him that ſent me, hath everlasting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but is paſſed from death to life,</hi> Joh. 5.24.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106746:14"/>from all this vve may cleerly ſee, that duties of obedience are required of beleevers, and they will be eaſily convinced of it, that are living members of the miſticall body of Chriſt, and living ſtones in his ſpirituall building; but for dead ſtones and empty trunkes, we wonder not much at their folly, which breaks out into all licentiouſneſſe and abominable practiſes; as for example, a woman proſtrating her ſelfe to uncleanneſſe, ſaid, you thinke that you ſhould ſinne if you ſhould lye with me; but what law doth forbid it unto us; O hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible practiſe of lawleſſe people! but when they ſee any to live as neer the rule of Gods law as they can, thoſe they reproach with ſuch names as theſe, duty-mongers, duty-doers, followers of legall preachers, ſcorning that word of God which condemnes their ſinfull courſes; and to expreſſe their diſlike of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of holineſſe, they ſay, What have we to doe with the dungie durty duties of ſanctification, we thanke God through Jeſus Chriſt we have nothing to doe with them; theſe they ſay are workes for home-booke Chriſtians; they tell us that beleevers doe duties onely in reſpect of men, for God requires none at their hands; they are ſo deluded that a woman ſaid, Jeſus Chriſt came and tooke her by the hand and asked her why ſhee was ſo ſad, and bad her leave off her mourning for ſinne and be cheerfull, for ſhee greatly diſhonoured the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in being troubled for her ſinnes: another, as ſhee was ſitting by the fire, Chriſt came to her and bad her pray for ſuch a one of her acquaintance, that ſhe may have aſſurance, which ſhe did, and preſently the party received by a light from Heaven full aſſurance: and another ſaid, nothing troubled her ſo much as the time ſhee had ſpent in prayer and other duties, which held her ſo long from her comfort: theſe are they that will not be guided by the law of God, who are given up to ſtrong deluſions to beleeve lyes, <hi>that they may be damned who beleeve not the truth,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.11, 12. But when theſe men with their owle eyes cannot abide the Sun-beames of cleare Scripture againſt them, they would hide themſelves with ſome humane teſtimonies, wreſted and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorted from the true meaning and intention of their alleadged Authors. Firſt, they boaſt highly that Maſter <hi>Luther</hi> is theirs wholly, and they hold nothing in this point, but what they ſucked from his breaſts; but by this inſtance you may ſee how they ſerve the reſt, for Maſter <hi>Luther</hi> was ſo farre from being an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomean, that no man doth more expreſly and ſoundly overthrow and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict this wicked opinion then he, neither can any man deſire a ſtronger humane witneſſe againſt them then Maſter <hi>Luther,</hi> read his words with a pauſe and judge; ſatan ſaith he ſtirreth up daily new Sects, and now he hath raiſed up a ſect of ſuch as teach that the ten Commandements are to be taken out of the Church, and that men ſhould not be terrified with the law; ſee this in <hi>Luthers</hi> Preface to his Commentary on the <hi>Gal.</hi> and in pag. 171. he ſpeaketh of three ſorts of men that abuſe the law; firſt, thoſe that ſeeke juſtification by the law; ſecondly, thoſe that will utterly exempt a Chriſtian man from the law; and on
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106746:14"/>page 153. he admoniſheth all thoſe that feare God, that they would learne out of <hi>Paul</hi> to underſtand the true and proper uſe of the law, which I feare ſaith he, after our time will be troden under foot and aboliſhed by the enemies of the truth; but if Maſter <hi>Luther</hi> thought that Chriſt had aboliſhed the law, he would never deſire men fearing God to learne the true uſe of it, and if he feared that men would aboliſh it, then ſure he thought in his judgement, that it ought not to be aboliſhed; and if he eſteeme them that would aboliſh it to be enemies to the truth, then ſure he is not their Patron, and in page 154. he ſaith, we doe plainly teſtifie that we reject not the law nor workes, as our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries doe falſly accuſe us, but we doe altogether eſtabliſh the law and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the workes thereof, and we ſay the law is good and profitable, and chap. 5.14. page 154. ſaith he, it is neceſſary that godly Preachers ſhould as diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teach the doctrine of good workes as the doctrine of faith; for ſatan is a deadly enemy of both; but then is <hi>Luther</hi> an Antinomean? doth he not directly contradict your fooliſh tenents, and diſclaime you as adverſaries and falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers: you reject the law and workes, but he rejecteth neither; you aboliſh the whole law, but he eſtabliſheth it; you reject them for legall preachers, that teach not Chriſt aright who urge men to the duties of the law, but he impoſeth it as a neceſſary part of their office to urge the law, as to teach the doctrine of faith: for ſhame never claime <hi>Luther</hi> more.</p>
               <p>But they object to ſmall purpoſe that <hi>Luther</hi> ſhould ſay, <hi>Chriſt hath aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed all the law of Moſes;</hi> ſo I ſay too, that he hath aboliſhed all the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> but they ſay he ſaith, pag 177. <hi>man is not justified by Gods law, nor mans law, but by Chriſt-alone,</hi> ſo I ſay too; but will it follow hence, that becauſe the law doth not juſtifie a ſinner therefore it is void, it is like as if a man ſhould ſay, that becauſe he cannot heare with his eyes, nor ſee with his eares, therefore they are all void and of no uſe to him; this is Antinome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an divinity.</p>
               <p>And ſo becauſe the terrours and torments of the law are taken off to belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, therefore the law is void to Antinomeans; if this be ſo, then if the ſting of death be taken off to beleevers, by their divinity they muſt not dye nor be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>courged for their ſinne; but as the ſting of death and afflictions is taken away to beleevers, and ſo they are ſweetned unto them, but not taken away, ſo the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urſe or ſting of the law is taken away, yet the law is not made void; and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne of <hi>Luthers</hi> Schollers ſaith, the Regenerate are not under the law, in reſpect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f juſtification, accuſation, condemnation or coaction; but he affirmeth a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>reefold uſe of the law to the Regenerate: Firſt, as a doctrine to direct in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es: Secondly, as a glaſſe to ſee the defects of them: Thirdly, to reſtrain cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ption that is in them. And Maſter <hi>Calvin</hi> in his ſecond book of Inſtitutions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 7. ſect. 12. ſpeakes of the morall law as it concernes the faithfull, how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey ſhould uſe it; namely, to know the will of God, and by the fervent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106746:15"/>of it, they ſhould be excited to the obedience of it, and ſtrengthened in their obedience of it, and reſtrained from the offences of it; in the 13. ſect. Libertines deny the law becauſe it is the miniſtration of death; but farre be it from us ſaith hee to hold ſuch a prophane opinion; he ſaith, it hath an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent uſe, namely, to be a perperuall rule of life, and ſo in the 14. and 15. ſect. and in the third booke 19. chap. ſect. 2. he ſaith, although Chriſtians muſt lift themſelves above the law, and forget the righteouſneſſe of the law; yet ſaith he, we muſt not conclude the law as needleſſe, for it doth not ceaſe to teach, to exhort, and to incite to good, though before Gods Tribunall, it hath no place in our conſciences; the law therefore by Maſter <hi>Calvins</hi> doctrine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, abideth by Chriſt an unviolable doctrine.</p>
               <p>I might mention many famous Divines, that have confuted this curſed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in their ſeveral ages, but I will only here mention one more to theſe two of famous memory in the Church of God becauſe their bookes are all extant and eaſie to be had, without much trouble to the Reader, it is that judicious Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> in his fruitfull writings appeareth every where as in his Golden-cheyn chap. 31. having ſet downe the uſe of the morall law in the unregenerate he concludeth, that the uſe of the law in the Regenerate is farre otherwiſe, for it guideth them to new obedience, which may be acceptable to God through Chriſt; and in his Commentary on the <hi>Gall.</hi> page 172. line 6. he ſheweth, that ſtill the Lord repeateth his law in his old tenure: Firſt, to teach us that the law is of a conſtant and unchangeable nature: Secondly, to advertiſe us of our weakneſſe, and to ſhew us what we cannot doe: Thirdly, to put us in mind ſtill to humble us, after we have begun by grace to obey the law, becauſe even then we came farre ſhort in doing the things which the law requireth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our hands; and on page 119. line 35. he enquireth, now faith is come, what i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the guard whereby we are now kept from ſinne? he anſwereth the morall law which is as ſtakes and nailes faſtened to range men in the compaſſe of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> owne duties, Eccleſ. 12.11. and upon page 201. line <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. he puts forth this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, how farre the morall law is abrogated; his anſwer is three wayes: Firſt in reſpect of juſtification: Secondly, of maladiction: Thirdly, in reſpect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> rigour; for them that are in Chriſt, God accepteth their endeavours to obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for obedience it ſelfe, nevertheleſſe ſaith he, the law as it is a rule of good li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is unchangeable and admitteth no abrogation, and Chriſt in this regard, did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his death eſtabliſh it, Rom. 3.31. and page 253. li. 35. he ſaith; the law muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> conſidered two wayes: Firſt, as a rule of life; thus Angels are under the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, and the Saints in Heaven and none yeeld more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jection to the law then they, and this ſubjection is their liberty,; but wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> did the Antinomeans learne this divinity? that Chriſt came to abrogate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> law of Innoce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cy, which <hi>Adam</hi> had before his fall, or the eternall law of Sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Angels glorified; alſo in his Treatiſe of conſcience, chap. 2. he ſaith; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106746:15"/>morall law bindeth the conſciences of all men and at all times to obedience. Now good Reader get theſe bookes, <hi>Calvins</hi> Inſtitutions and <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> on the <hi>Galla.</hi> and ſee theſe things that thou maieſt be ſatisfied, and ſhake off theſe ſeducers, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſhook off the Viper, Acts 28.5. leſt thou periſh eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally by them.</p>
               <p>Well, thus we have driven them from their ſtrong holds, the Scripture is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and good men forſake them, for they have made lyes their refuge, and under falſhood have they hid themſelves; but the haile ſhall ſweep away their refuge of lyes, and the waters ſhall overflow their hiding place, Iſa. 28.15.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But when thou art spoyled, what wilt thou doe? though thou cloatheſt thy ſelfe with Crimſon, though thou deckeſt thy ſelfe with Ornaments of gold, though thou painteſt thy face with painting, in vaine ſhalt thou make thy ſelfe faire, thy lovers will despiſe thee,</hi> Jer. 4.30. Thou art called to give an account of thy Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, art thou reſolved what to doe? that when thou art put out, thy Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean proſelites may receive thee into their houſes, Luke 16.2.4. thou haſt but one ſhift more, that when thy Maſters debters are called, to deny half their debt, to take their bill and preſently diſcharge them of all their debt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the old Teſtament; and if this will not pleaſe them to receive thee, when God and good men have caſt thee off, then take thy bill and write pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently <hi>ſcriptum eſt,</hi> any thing is ſcripture, and of an equall vallue with it, if it be but written in a play booke or ballad, if this will not doe to be maintained privately amongſt them, tell them that thou knoweſt no word of God, but Chriſt and this word is in thee, and therefore thou needeſt no other helpe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thou art ſo full of light within; theſe things comes next to be anſwered.</p>
               <p>They deny utterly the authority of the old Teſtament; yet this need not to trouble us, when as it is ſo abundantly confirmed both by Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the new, not onely by coating of it, but giving it the name and title of Scripture; <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of Geneſis, ſaith, <hi>What ſaith the ſcripture?</hi> Abraham <hi>beleeved God,</hi> Rom. 4.3. and of Exodus, <hi>The Scripture ſaith unto Pharaoh,</hi> Rom. 9.17. and of Numbers, <hi>that the ſcripture might be fulfilled,</hi> John 19.36. and of Deuteronomie, <hi>as the ſcripture hath ſaid,</hi> John 7.38. and of Iſaiah, <hi>the ſcripture ſaith,</hi> Rom. 10.11. and of the Pſalmes, <hi>that the ſcripture might be fulfilled,</hi> and of Zechariah, <hi>another ſcripture ſaith,</hi> John 19.24.28.47. what ſhall I ſay? Chriſt beginning at <hi>Moſes,</hi> and all the Prophets, expounded unto them in all the Scriptures the things concerning himſelf, then opened he their underſtanding that they may know the Scriptures, what was written in the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the Prophets and Pſalmes concerning himſelfe, Luke 24.27.44, 45. ſaith Chriſt, ſearch the Scriptures for they teſtifie of me, John 3.39. now I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what Scriptures theſe were, if not the old Teſtament, for the new was not yet written? and ſo <hi>Apollos</hi> mighty in Scripture convinced the Jewes,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106746:16"/>
                  <hi>ſhewing by the ſeripture that Jeſus was Chriſt,</hi> Acts 18.24.28. <hi>and all that was written aforetime was for our learning that we through patience and comfort of the ſcriptures might have hope,</hi> Rom. 15.4. then how dare theſe men deny the old Teſtament that is ſo confirmed both by Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the new, which is the language of their Honey-combe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Some Errours that are in a little booke called the <hi>Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evill,</hi> diſcovered and anſwered.</head>
               <p>IN that Book they make any humane writings to be Scripture, and make no difference betweene play-bookes and the Scripture of truth, Dan. 10.21. <hi>but all Scripture is given by anspiration, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproofe, for correction, for instruction in righteouſneſſe, that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good workes, and the Scripture is able to make thee wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.15, 16, 17. then are the writings of men ſuch a Scripture? Again, the Scripture is of no private interpretation, <hi>For the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie came not in old time by the will of men, but holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy-Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.20.21. then is mens writings Scripture? <hi>He that ſhall adde to this Booke, God will adde to him all the plagues that are written in this Booke; or if any man ſhall take away any thing from the words of this Booke. God ſhall take away his part out of the Booke of life,</hi> Rev. 22.18, 19. then ſurely the two Teſtaments with all their ſeverall Chapters, contained in them, are the Scripture, and not any humane writings whatſoever.</p>
               <p>But I fear any Scripture may ſerve them that regard none at all, for they ſay, that they are led onely by an inward Principle, ſo that they need no other help at all; but the noble Bereans did ſearch the Scripture daily to ſee whither thoſe things were ſo, Act. 17.11. the Scriptures ſhould be the ſole Judge of all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies and that by which we ſhould try all our thoughts, words, and actions; therefore ſaith Chriſt <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> Joh. 5.39. <hi>To the law, &amp; to the teſt: mony, if they ſpeak not according to that, it is becauſe there is no light in them,</hi> Iſ. 8.20. for the Pen-men of it could not erre in writing of it, <hi>the Apostles were filled with the Holy-ghoſt, &amp; they ſpake as the Spirit gave them utterance,</hi> Act. 2.4 and when they mention that which is written in the old Teſtament, they ſay, <hi>thus ſaith the Holy-ghost,</hi> Heb. 3.7. <hi>and well ſpake the Holy-ghost,</hi> Act. 28.5. <hi>He ſpake by the mouth of his holy Prophets ſince the world began,</hi> Luk. 1.70. therfore when theſe men ſay the law is written in their hearts, &amp; they need not the law in the letter of it, <hi>they do erre not knowing the Scriptures,</hi> Mat. 22.29. they think becauſe they ſee the act of murther and theft are ſins, therefore they ſee enough, but ſo much a carnall man may ſee with that remainder or reliques of the law that was in <hi>Adams</hi> heart, &amp; many do by nature the things contained in the law, which ſhew the work of the law written in their hearts, Rom. 2.14.15. but yet. <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:106746:16"/>did not ſee the luſt of heart to be a ſinne, but by the written law, Rom. 7.7. we know but in part, and we ſee but darkly as through a glaſſe, 1 Cor. 13.12. we ſee Chriſt but through the lettice, Cant. 2.9. and when we ſee our ſinnes by the law, if we doe not continue therein, we ſoone forget what manner of men we were, James 1.24.25. then let us obey that command, and write us a coppy of the law, and read therein all the dayes of our life, Deut. 17.18.19. and <hi>the heart of man is deceitfull above all things, and who can know it?</hi> Jer. 17.9. then we had need to try our ſelves daily by the written law of God, that we turne not aſide from it, and ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> not as though I had already attained or were already perfect; but I follow after brethren, I count not my ſelfe to have apprehended but I forget theſe things behind, and preſſe toward the marke; nevertheleſſe whereunto we have attained, let us walke by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame thing, Phil. 3.12, 13, 14, 15. and as many as obey this rule, peace be on them and mercy, Gal. 6.16.</p>
               <p>Againe, they ſay there is no other word of God but Chriſt, becauſe <hi>in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God, and the word was made fleſh,</hi> John 1.1.14. but Chriſt is in them and ſo the Word is perfectly in them, and they neither know nor need any other: It is true Chriſt is the eſſentiall word of God, being the ſecond perſon in Trinity, but he is not the written word of God contained in letters and ſillables, which are Gods owne words, although many of them were ſpoken by men: for it is ſaid, <hi>God ſpake all theſe words and ſaid,</hi> Exod. 20.1. <hi>then bleſſed are they that heare the word of God and keepe it,</hi> Luke 11.28. and againe Chriſt ſaid, <hi>you are cleane through the word that I have ſpoken unto you,</hi> Iohn 15.3. <hi>and Chriſt will ſanctifie his Church by the waſhing of water with the word,</hi> Ephe. 5.26. but neither water nor word were his perſon, it were folly to thinke ſo, <hi>then let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly,</hi> Col. 3.16. <hi>he that heareth my word and beleeveth in him that ſent me, hath everlasting life,</hi> John 5.24. his ſheep heare his voyce and follow him; <hi>they have</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets, let them heare them,</hi> for they all ſpake, Thus ſaith the Lord; and the word of the Lord came unto me ſaying, <hi>but if they will not heare</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets, neither will they be perſwaded though one roſe from the dead.</hi> Luke 16.29.31.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Some other Errours I find in a little Booke Intitled, <hi>Chriſts counſell to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the Church of Laodicea,</hi> diſcovered and anſwered: they ſay that le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall teachers ſay, God will not ſave us without faith, and repentance, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, ſelf deniall, fasting, mourning, and prayer, and the uſe of the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as hearing, reading, and receiving the Sacraments, and obſerving the Sab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bath, and doing as we would be done by, and a deſire to keepe all Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and yeelding univerſall obedience thereto, and to hate all ſinne.</head>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:106746:17"/>
               <p>THe Antinomeans ſay, that they are bewitched that hold a man cannot be ſaved without faith, and wiſheth them cut off that ſo trouble them; they ſay it is the envious man that hath ſowed thoſe Tares, but here he cals the Spirit of God that envious man, becauſe he hath told us, that without faith it is unpoſſible to pleaſe God, Heb. 11.16. <hi>and whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne,</hi> Rom. 14.23. <hi>and he that beleeveth not is damned already, and the wrath of God abideth on him,</hi> John 3.18.36.</p>
               <p>Then what a bold blaſphemer is this, to call the holy Spirit of God the envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, becauſe he contradicts their curſed Errours: They ſay, why ſhould Chriſt put them upon the performance of conditions, they having no life but are ſtone-dead in ſinne? ſo I ſay too; but when Chriſt gives us a hand, and life, and motion in it too, it is no hard condition to put it out to receive ſo great a Benefit. He ſaith, for God to put us upon ſuch a worke ſupernaturall as faith is, and to have no part in Chriſt without it, ſeems very difficult and unlike his Fatherly affections toward us: I anſw. but Gods people doe not thinke ſo whatever he thinkes; when God hath given them faith they muſt uſe it, and cannot doe otherwiſe, they find ſo much profit and comfort by implying that Tallent of faith.</p>
               <p>He ſaith, to ſay faith is a condition without which we cannot be ſaved, doth perplex the conſcience, and denies our mercies and reſiſts the ſpirit of God, and doth not conſiſt with the right end; for which faith was wrought in us; he ſaith, Chriſt died for the ungodly to purchaſe remiſſion of ſinnes, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile them to God; and ſo I ſay too, ſo it be underſtood out of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Elect, but when he ſaith this was done without any condition or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication on our parts; we remaining ungodly ſtill, and going on in a courſe of ſinnes is a foule errour; but I have anſwered it already: and he ſaith, faith was given that we might ſee what was wrought in and upon us, before we had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faith or calling; that is ſaith he, to ſee our remiſſion of ſinnes, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with God, and how we are made righteous in the ſight of God, juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and ſaved; all this as ſoone as we have our being in this life, and faith is but a declarative grace to ſhew us theſe things that were all done before, but onely we did not ſee them, and ſo faith comforts us, ſaith he; and when the law clamours for obedience, faith anſwers, we are not under the law but under grace, and therefore they owe no obedience to it; it is true, they will doe ſome things unrequired, as to breake out into exaltations and thankfulneſſe, but not as any duty they owe to the Lord, but upon free will and as a curtiſie, what they pleaſe unrequired; this is their free grace, but it is of the divels making to damne their ſoules; but <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Chriſt was revealed for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.26. and he received grace and Apoſtleſhip for the obedience of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. they ſay that their love makes them doe great
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106746:17"/>matters unrequired; but let them take heed how they bring ſtrange fire or any thing, before they have tryed it in the ballance of the Sanctuary, for God will not be ſerved by their deviſings, but by his owne directions made knowne to us in his law, <hi>He that looketh into the perfect law of liberty and continueth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, not being a forgetfull hearer but a doer of the worke, this man is bleſſed in the deed,</hi> James 1.25. we muſt bring that worſhip and ſervice that God requires in his law for ſubſtance, and in the ſame manner it muſt be done in faith, and time, &amp; place conſidered; and to the ſame end, that God hath apointed, which is, his glory; but their faith ſheweth them a Chriſt that requires no duty of them, but what they pleaſe out of free love and curtiſie, for all was done before they had faith or calling; and he ſaith, children when they dye are ſaved without faith; but I ſuppoſe that to be more then he can prove, becauſe without faith it is unpoſſible to pleaſe God, <hi>and he that beleeveth not is damned already, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he wrath of God abideth on him;</hi> but that wrath muſt be removed, and they muſt pleaſe God before they can be ſaved, although we cannot conceive the manner how it is wrought in them, therefore when Chriſt came to heale any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſeaſes, if he perceived they had faith to be healed, then he cured them, and commonly he ſaid, according to thy faith be it unto thee, all things are poſſible to him that beleeveth: he ſaith, they that mix the Law and the Goſpell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are falſe teachers; and ſo I ſay too, and to make redemption conditionall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o depend on duties as cauſes, I ſay the ſame; but to ſay theſe duties are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>equired as the way to ſalvation, is a groſſe errour, that beats off all obedience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the law of God; but they ſay, the ſtate of a Chriſtian is moſt free in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, becauſe nothing at all is required of him; and he ſaith, they are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that teach otherwiſe, ſo that their free grace they boaſt ſo much of, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a freedome from all obedience to the lavv of God.</p>
               <p>I find in that book of theirs, that they ſay, legall Teachers ſay, <hi>that repentance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umiliation, ſelf-deniall, weeping, mourning, faſting and praying, and the uſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Sacraments, the obſerving of the Sabbath, and doing as one would be done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto, and the reſt, muſt be done as duties, but are palpable mistakings, for they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re made as duties by almoſt all Teachers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here they ſhew their ſinne as <hi>Sodome,</hi> and bewray what they meane by <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir free grace; yet I ſay againe, that we deny that duties are any cauſes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur ſalvation, but they are the way appointed by the Lord to attaine that end, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd muſt be done in obedience to Gods command, and not left for us to doe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not to doe at our pleaſure; theſe ought to be preſſed as duties, ſo long as we <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rry about with us daily a body of ſinne; which is as a heavy weight upon us; <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d being alwayes with us, and makes us faile in all our duties; we then had <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed to be ſtirred up daily to weeping and mourning and to repent of our fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gs; nay, although we know nothing by our ſelves, yet are we not hereby ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106746:18"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. becauſe there be many ſecret ſinnes in us that we cannot find out, <hi>O Lord forgive our ſecret ſins,</hi> Pſal. 19. he ſaith, feare hath torment; ſo I ſay that ſlaviſh feare hath torment, and is not made perfect in love, 1 Joh. 4.18. but filiall feare is a companion of all joy and comfort, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.11.56.6. he ſaith, it is in vaine to bid a beleever humble himſelfe, for there is none ſo humble as he. But is this an argument ſufficient, why beleevers ſhould not be called upon to humble themſelves, becauſe others are not humbled? and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſee others are worſe then themſelves? but this is their folly; who have left the law of God which is the true rule, and make ſinfull men their rule, and ſo the blind lead the blind, till both fall into the ditch. But we muſt not follow the Antinomeans rule, ſo long as we have the true rule to walke by, which is the perfect and eternall law of God, this glaſſe of Gods law will ſhew us our ſinnes; <hi>I had not knowne ſinne but by the law,</hi> Rom. 7.7. <hi>for by the law is the knowledge of ſinne,</hi> Rom. 3.20. and it was after <hi>Pauls</hi> converſion, that he looked upon the law and came to know his ſinne, which ſhews that he had not done with it when he beleeved, and are we more perfect then he?</p>
               <p>Although a beleever comes to ſee his owne vileneſſe, and therefore denies himſelfe, and no man more, yet he is but part ſpirit and part fleſh, and theſe two are fighting continually in him, and we ſee the often fals of the beſt of Gods people, which ſhould be a warning to us to walke circumſpectly, not as fooles but as wiſe, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.15. we had need be ready and willing both to give coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and to receive counſell, to walke watchfully and humbly, <hi>let us conſider on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> another, and provoke unto love and to good workes,</hi> Heb. 10.24. <hi>Paul</hi> bids <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy to ſtirre up that gift that was given him,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.6. and <hi>Paul</hi> with ſtood <hi>Peter to his face, becauſe he was to be blamed; and</hi> Barnabas <hi>was carrie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> away alſo with their diſſimulation,</hi> Gal. 2.11.13.</p>
               <p>Then ſure <hi>Paul</hi> was no Antinomean, that ſtirs up their dull ſpirits to their duties of obedience and watchfulneſſe; neither was <hi>Barnabas,</hi> nor <hi>Timothy,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the reſt Antinomeans, that ſtood in need of the helpe of others, when one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them his graces ſeemed to dye within him, and the other almoſt loſt, till <hi>Pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> rouſed them up againe; then take notice of this prophane man, how his fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grace gives way freely to all manner of ſinnes in beleevers, when he ſaith, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> need not bid them to humble themſelves; what is this but to make void a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtian duties, and for mourning for ſinne and faſting? when the Bride<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/> groome ſeemes to be taken away from them, and his faith is clouded, you nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not to bid them faſt and mourne, for (ſaith he) they are too apt and too pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to wrong themſelves thereby; and ſo in the matter of repentance.</p>
               <p>Therefore rather reprove them that doe ſo for their weakneſſe; but mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we beleeve this Antinomean, rather then the Bridegroome himſelfe? wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaith, <hi>the dayes will come, when the Bridegroome ſhall be taken away from them
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106746:18"/>and then ſhall they faſt in thoſe dayes,</hi> Luke 5.35, ſurely if this man had known what it had beene to have his faith clouded, and the loving countenance of God hidden from him, it would make him faſt, and mourne, and weepe, <hi>to have thoſe joyes restored againe, that the broken bones may rejoyce,</hi> Pſal. 51.8.12. and although this man would have them reproved that doe ſo, yet Chriſt bids them <hi>aske and ye ſhall have, ſeeke and ye ſhall find, k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke and it ſhall be opened; hitherto ye have asked nothing, aske that your joy may be full,</hi> John 16.24. he ſaith, a child that knowes that his Father loves him, ſhall you need to tell him that he ought in duty to aske it of his Father; as much need ſaith he, is there to preach prayer as a duty; but curſed be he that denies that prayer to God, both for himſelfe and others to be a duty; ſaith <hi>Samuel, God forbid that J ſhould ſinne againſt the Lord, in ceaſing to pray for you,</hi> 1 Sam. 12.23. and how frequent have the Saints in all ages beene in this duty, both for themſelves and others; but yet I confeſſe that ſuch as they are, <hi>who turne away their care from hearing the law, their prayer is abomination,</hi> Prov. 28.9. now if they be ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of this heavy ſentence, they are wiſer then I tooke them to be, to ſave themſelves that labour, when their prayer is nothing worth, becauſe they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the law of God.</p>
               <p>But they ſay, a beleever cannot want much nor many things, therefore they need not pray: I anſw. Although a beleever be rich, yet he hath it not in his owne keeping; he hath exceeding great and precious promiſes, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. but we muſt fetch out theſe things, as we have occaſion by the prayer of faith; thus ſaith the Lord God, <hi>Yet I will be ſought for of the houſe of Iſrael,</hi> Ezek. 36.37. <hi>aske of me and I will give thee,</hi> Pſal. 2.8. and ſometimes <hi>Dives</hi> hath his good things; and <hi>Lazarus</hi> his evill things, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.25. becauſe God loves to hear his people pray, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.8. But then ſaith this man, if they doe pray, ſure a very ſhort prayer may ſerve their turne, as our Saviour well knew when he taught us how to pray, and reproved long prayer; here this man ſheweth all his heart, then ſee how he ſuckes poyſon out of the ſweeteſt Flowers, as <hi>the Roſe of Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and the Lilly of the Vallies,</hi> Cant. 2.1. he turnes the meaning of Chriſt himſelfe to his owne corrupted humour, as all Heretiques uſe to doe.</p>
               <p>For Chriſt did but teach them the ground of all prayer, but when he ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to pray, <hi>he continued all night in prayer to God,</hi> Luke 6.12. <hi>When</hi> Peter <hi>was in priſon, prayer was made without ceaſing to God for him,</hi> Acts 12.5. <hi>men ought alwayes to pray and not faint,</hi> Luke 18.1. <hi>Cornelius</hi> prayed alwayes, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.2. Then did all theſe ſay nothing but that we call the Lords Prayer, and then ceaſe, or did they ſay it over as many times as a Fryar will tye his whore to ſay it, to ſatisfie for her whoredome; which is their folly.</p>
               <p>Neither did Chriſt intend to reprove long prayers, but when they asked vaine petitions, or when they ſtand in the ſtreet to be ſeene of men, or when
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106746:19"/>they are large in their owne ſutes, and will not heare the complaint of poore Widdowes, but are ready to devour them, <hi>theſe ſhall receive greater damnation</hi> Mat. 23.14.</p>
               <p>But this Antinomean ſaith, <hi>if we aske any thing it is a vaine petition, becauſe we beleeve that we have it already; as to aske for remiſſion of ſinne, and crying out of the burthen of ſinne, when we beleeve that Chriſt hath bourne our ſinnes in his body on the Tree, and that his blood cleanſeth us from all ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer; although we beleeve that all our ſinnes paſt are remitted, yet we ſinne daily, therefore Chriſt hath taught us daily to aske forgiveneſſe. Againe, a man ſometimes hath ſome one ſinne that troubleth him, that he hath no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine aſſurance of the pardon of it at the preſent; as <hi>David</hi> after the ſinne of murther, prayes the Lord to take away blood guiltineſſe from him, Pſ. 51.14. although <hi>Nathan</hi> had told him before that it was forgiven, 2 Sam. 12.13.</p>
               <p>But he ſaith, <hi>he that prayes for the pardon of his ſinne, is like a man afrighted with ſinne, and at the ſame time giving thankes for the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>miſion of ſinne, and of a man that is afraid of the ſinnes of his preſent prayers, and of one that hath victory over ſinne, death, and hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer; although our ſinnes be pardoned and the guilt taken away, yet the being of ſinne is not taken away; and although we are juſtified from all ſinne, yet we are not ſanctified from all ſinne; ſo that we ought to be humbled for our filthineſſe for want of ſanctification when we come into the preſence of God; and becauſe that ſinne is in us, we may well feare that we ſhall not carry our ſelves ſo holy, as becometh ſuch a preſence, as the men of <hi>Beth-ſhemiſh</hi> ſaid, <hi>Who is able to ſtand before this holy Lord God?</hi> 1 Sam. 6.20. and yet not ſo deſpaire as to leave off the duty, but to pray ſtill; and as ſanctification increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, we come into the preſence of God with more cheerfulneſſe, and as our aſſurance increaſeth, we ſhall be leſſe in our petitions and more in thankſgiving and praiſing God for his mercies to us.</p>
               <p>He ſaith, <hi>we preſent a man that is delivered from the law, into the glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the ſonnes of God, and yet puts himſelfe under the law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer; we are delivered from the curſes of the law, and the threatnings of the lavv, and from the condemning povver of it, and from the conſtraining povver of it, but vve are not delivered from the commanding povver of it, the free grace of Chriſt did not deliver us from our obedience to the lavv of God; but in giving us the eye of faith vve ſee our duty more cleerly that is vvritten in the lavv of God, and by our hand of faith vve fetch more ſtrength from Chriſt to enable us to performe our duty to the lavv of God, <hi>I can do all things through Chriſt that ſtrengtheneth me,</hi> Phil. 4.13. but if our eye of faith vvere never ſo cleere to ſee our duty, yet if vve vvill not looke upon the lavv of God but count it as a ſtrange thing, Hoſea 8.12. it is all one to them, as if the book
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106746:19"/>of the law were ſealed up; and he that hath no faith, is like a man to whom the booke of the law is open, but the man cannot read for he is not learned, Iſa. 29.11, 12. ſo then the eye of faith is the Organ, and our duty is the object, and the written law of God is the Medium by which we ſee our duty; but when the law is taken from us, or if we caſt away the commanding power of it, which is all one we can ſee our duty no more then a man can ſee in a dungeon; then well may the Antinomians be ſo blind concerning their duty, when as they caſt away that light that ſhould ſhew it unto them, <hi>thy law is a lanterne to my feet, and a light unto my pathes,</hi> Pſal. 119.105.</p>
               <p>But then faith hath another property, when it ſees the greatneſſe of the work to be done, and the weakneſſe of the doer of it, that it ſeeth helpe in another which is Chriſt, and preſently fetcheth it to helpe him, <hi>this honour have all the Saints,</hi> Pſal. 149.9.</p>
               <p>He ſaith, <hi>we need not to tell a healthfull man that it is his duty to feed himſelf, even ſo is it needfull to tell a beleever that it is his duty to heare Sermons, read the Scripture, and frequent the Lords Table, theſe are his proper and his naturall food, by which his faith is ſtrengthened and increaſed; yet (ſaith he) in what a ſad and fearfull manner are theſe preſſed upon mens conſciences, upon paine of having no part in Chriſt, and of everlasting damnation in hell for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer; firſt, if one ſhould tell a healthfull man that it is his duty to feed himſelfe, I hope it would not make him leave feeding and goe about to ſtarve himſelfe, becauſe he is told that he muſt doe it as a duty; and ſo for ſpirituall duties to be told of them is rather an encouragement to goe on ſtill, becauſe it is their duty; and what if he know it before? he need not be offended at the love of his friend, for telling him that which he knew before; but I ſmell wherein lieth the venome of this man, he hath free grace beſtowed on him which hath freed him from all duties of obedience to the Lord, ſo that what he doth, is onely out of free love; for he thinkes to be tyed by way of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will not ſtand with his free grace; but I ſay againe, we truſt in no duty as cauſes of our ſalvation, but we obey and doe theſe duties as the way to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; neither did they ever heare thoſe worthy Divines, whom they villefie with the termes of legall Teachers, preſſe any duties to merit ſalvation for the doing of them; but let the ſonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> know, that if they ſlight their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the law of God, they may purchaſe damnation by it; neither can there be any ſalvation for that man till he humble himſelfe, and freely yeeld to the commanding power of the law of God, and count it his duty to give all the power of body and ſoule in obedience to it; but this yoke is too heavy for the ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> they will be tyed to nothing but upon free love and curriſie, that they may leave it when they liſt; they have gotten free grace.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:106746:20"/>
               <p>He ſaith, <hi>they put us upon theſe duties to try and to prove our ſelves by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of them, as by markes and ſignes of grace within.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer; if Chriſt be in the ſoule, there muſt needs be fignes of his preſence; we need not goe by heare-ſay or from a bare Teſtimony or ſuggeſtion; they told <hi>Jacob</hi> that <hi>Joſeph</hi> was alive, but that did not ſatisfie him till he ſaw the Wagons, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.27.28. ſo now if the eyes of the ſoule be opened to ſee our duty written in the law, it is Chriſt that hath done it, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14. <hi>whoſe heart the Lord opened:</hi> Doe ye aske whence he is? <hi>and yet he hath opened mine eyes,</hi> John 9.30. Acts 26.17, 18. Secondly, the worke muſt ariſe from a true juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith, that knits them to Chriſt and makes their perſon accepted, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4. this faith muſt take hold of that promiſe that is made to them that doe this duty, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.6. Thirdly, in our duties we muſt aime at Gods glory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. thus by any duty we may try our ſelves whether we doe it by vertue of Gods command without us, and whether it be acted by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward principle of faith within us, and whether it tend to Gods glory as the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt end of it; he that hath theſemarkes and ſignes the Spirit of God is in him, this faith worketh by love and obedience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5.1 <hi>John</hi> 5.3. neither can he ſay, what a fearfull thing it is to preſſe theſe things as duties upon our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that belongs to the ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> that cannot abide the yoke of Gods ſaw, that requires thoſe duties of them.</p>
               <p>He ſaith, <hi>the true beleever ſubmits himſelfe to every Ordinance of man;</hi> mark a little the reaſoning of this miſguided man; he that ſaid before, that beleevers muſt not ſubmit to the lawes of God, now he ſaith they muſt ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it to the lawes of man; and he that denied obedience to Gods lawes, was any marke or ſigne of a beleever; yet he ſaith, <hi>he that ſubmits to mans Ordinance is a true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever:</hi> but yet here is more venome behind in this argument, for what is this Ordinance of man? He ſaith <hi>it is the obſervation of the Sabbath ſo exceedingly preached and preſt as a duty, to be exactly performed in the exerciſe onely of the worſhip and ſervice of God;</hi> thus caſting aſperſion upon the Lords day, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his worſhip and ſervice, calling it mans ordinance, becauſe he would over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Sabbath of the Lord, and then he goes about to ſet up his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention; in the next words ſaying, <hi>all dayes are to him, this Sabbath, for he liveth in that reſt that was tipified out of the old Sabbath;</hi> he ſaith, <hi>he will take care to keepe faith in heart, and breath, and faith will make every day a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, now he hath Chriſt, for the ſhadow is gone, the body is Chriſt, his free grace hath freed him from keeping a ſabbath, for it is but the Ordinance of man:</hi> here he contradicts his owne Character of a true beleever, which was to ſubmit to mans Ordinance; but here is a true Character of one, ſwarving from the true rule, which is the law of God, and now he walks in crooked pathes of his owne
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106746:20"/>invention, playing the hipocrit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaying, <hi>although he ſubmit the outward man, the inward man cannot be beguiled:</hi> here you ſee as rotten a heart diſcovered, as ever lived in man, ſome heretiques deny one Commandement, ſome ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but never any denied them all, till this curſed hereſie ſprung up; but let them read the judgements of God on Sabbath breakers, &amp; the <hi>Practice of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> the one to whip them, and the other to ſhew them their duty, if perhaps the thoughts of their heart may be forgiven them; take heed, leſt you with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts deny the Lordſhip of Chriſt, who cleared the law from all falſe gloſſes, and gave it them in his owne name, ſhewing the ſtrictneſſe of it, reaching not onely to the outward man, but rectifying the ſoule and inward parts of man, and ſo to bring all parts of body and ſoule in obedience and free ſubjection to it, and that for ever.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>In the entrance of any anſwer to the firſt errour in this booke, I left the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God till faith and calling, becauſe I would barre them from flying thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be they will want courage, to face the Canon of Gods Word, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for ſhelter to the dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ees of God; and ſay God hath decreed to juſtifie them before faith or calling; but theſe ſigge leaves will not cover their naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for did God decree to ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ifie them, and then decree to give them faith and to call them? this is but another errour; for doubtleſſe God decreed to give his people faith, and to call them at the ſame time when he decreed to juſtifie them, and all with one ſimple act from all eternity; but what meanes thoſe other words? they are juſtified as ſoone as they have any being; will they ſay the child muſt firſt be borne before God decree to ſave it? and if they ſay by this word being, they meane in the decree of God, then I demand, what they meane by thoſe words, as ſoone as they had any, &amp;c. will they ſay, there was time beyond the decree of God, thus they are in a circle not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where to get out. This ſhould have beene inſerted at the end of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the firſt Errour, Pag 6.</p>
            <p>Good Reader, I pray thee correct ſuch faults in this Booke, as by overſight hath eſcaped the Preſſe; as page 2. line 17. for righteouſneſſe, read righteouſneſſes, and for the Title on certaine pages, a briefe Anſwer, read a briefe and plaine Anſwer; and for the names of thoſe that profeſſe this hereſie here condemned, for Antenomeans and Antinomeans, read Antinomians.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
